<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A learned and profitable treatise of mans iustification Two bookes. Opposed to the sophismes of Robert Bellarmine, Iesuite. By Iohn Piscator, professor of diuinitie in the famous schools of Nassouia Sigena.</title>
            <title>Learned and profitable treatise of mans justification.</title>
            <author>Piscator, Johannes, 1546-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102907</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838668</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838668</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3055</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09695)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3055)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1149:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A learned and profitable treatise of mans iustification Two bookes. Opposed to the sophismes of Robert Bellarmine, Iesuite. By Iohn Piscator, professor of diuinitie in the famous schools of Nassouia Sigena.</title>
                  <title>Learned and profitable treatise of mans justification.</title>
                  <author>Piscator, Johannes, 1546-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Creede, for Ralphe Iackson, dwelling in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Swanne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of iustification.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3055:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3055:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3055:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3055:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LEARNED AND PROFITABLE Treatiſe of mans <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two Bookes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oppoſed to the Sophiſmes of <hi>Robert Bellarmine,</hi> Ieſuite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Iohn Piſcator, <hi>profeſſor of Diuinitie in the famous Schoole of</hi> Naſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia Sigena.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Thomas Creede, for Raphe Iackſon, dwelling in Paules Chruch-yard at the ſigne of the Swanne. 1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3055:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3055:3"/>
            <head>TO THE REVEREND and renowmed men, <hi>Daniel Toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanus, Iames Kimedoncius,</hi> and <hi>Dauid Pareus:</hi> Doctors of ſacred Theology, and profeſſors in the famous Vniuerſitie of <hi>Heidelberg:</hi> his high-eſteemed brethren, greeting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith how great endeuor &amp; ſubtilly deuiſed and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed Sophiſmes, <hi>Robert Bellarmine</hi> Ieſuite, hath ſtudied to cloake and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Popiſh errours: and contrariwiſe, to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate and refute the doctrine of the true teachers of the Goſpell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Christian faith: it is knowne to them that haue read with iudgement, his diſputations of the articles in controuerſie betweene the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and the Goſpellers, whom he falſly calleth hereticks. Theſe diſputations, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not long ſince they came alſo to my handes. I read them deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, and was not a litle greened, when I ſawe the truth of the Goſpel to be with ſuch a ſhewe oppugned. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I remembred how I heard of a credible man, that learned men addicted to the Popiſh religion, ſo greatly boasted of this
<pb facs="tcp:3055:4"/>
               <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> as if he were ſome <hi>Goliath</hi> of the Papiſts, that they feared not to ſay he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible: I began earneſtly to deſire that God wold ſtirre vp many of the teachers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, valiantly &amp; happily to withſtand the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes of this <hi>Goliath,</hi> &amp; with the ſtone of Gods word handſomely throwne out of the ſling of true Logicke, to fell him downe, and finally, to kill him with his owne ſword. And I gaue God thankes, that euen then he had ſtirred vp ſome learned men which had prosperouſly begun this fight with him: among whom firſt was knowne vnto me, that famous man <hi>William Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> who fought with him manfully and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about the holy ſcripture, and purpoſed alſo to dispute againſt him about other chiefe points in controuerſie. God the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, graunt that what he hath holily purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, he may prosperouſly bring to effect.</p>
            <p>But when as about the ſame time I was to write and propound for publicke disputation in the famous ſchoole of <hi>Naſſouia Herborne,</hi> poſitions of Iuſtification, I thought it would be worth my labour, diligently to inquire into <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines</hi> ſophiſmes, publiſhed concerning that article of faith, and to endeuour briefly &amp; plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to refute them. And by this occaſion was this my writing brought forth, which now I publiſh abroad. Which when for the length thereof I
<pb facs="tcp:3055:4"/>ſaw not meet to be propoſed for Poſitions pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to bee diſputed of in the ſchoole, I then wrote and ſet out other poſitions of Iuſtification: and reſerued this writing for a more fit time. It fell out about the ſame time, that the learned man <hi>Corradus Vorſtius Agrippenſis,</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among you and of you a while after. Doctor of Theologie, deſired by Letters mine opinion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſoluting one or two of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> ſophiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in the controuerſie of Iustification: vnto whom I ſent to that end this writing: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, requeſted him to communicate it with lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, of which your Vniuerſitie hath ſtore, and to knowe their iudgements of it, and write me word. He therefore of late about <hi>Francfurt</hi> Mart, paſſing by <hi>Sigena,</hi> and for the friendſhip betwixt vs, ſaluting me, told me how he had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you this writing of mine to reade; and that you hauing read it, affirmed vnto him that you liked all therein, and would exhort me to ſet it forth, diſtinguiſhed into two Bookes and certain Chapters: which thing alſo hee wrote of to me not long after from <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> and ſo ſtirred me vp a freſh to diualge this writing. Now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore commeth this my writing forth in the name of the Lord: and it commeth forth vnder your excellent name: for that I thought I ſhould doo conueniently, to offer this doctrine to be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by them (togither with my ſelfe) which had
<pb facs="tcp:3055:5"/>once approoued it for a good and right opinion: and therwithal publikely to teſtifie our holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in this heauenly truth. You therefore reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend brethren, take this my doing in good part: and valiantly defend as oft as need ſhal require, togither with me, the trueth of Christian doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine deliuered in this writing: to the glorie of Gods name, and profit of Chriſts Church. To conclude, I commend you and your holy labours to God, the Father of our Lord Ieſus Christ. At <hi>Sigena,</hi> from the famous Schoole of <hi>Naſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia,</hi> the <hi>18.</hi> of December, <hi>1594.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Brother,</hi> Iohn Piſcator, <hi>of Argentine.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3055:5"/>
            <head>OF MANS IVSTIFICATION before God.</head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <head>
                  <hi>The firſt booke.</hi> VVherein the iudgement of the <hi>profeſſors of the Goſpell is recited,</hi> confirmed and defended <hi>from</hi> Bellarmines exceptions.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the diuers ſignifications of the word <hi>Iuſtifying.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen it is demaunded, how a man may be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed before God: the word <hi>Iustifie</hi> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken two wayes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time for to make or to be made iuſt: and ſometime for to pronounce, or to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced iuſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3055:6"/>
Theſe two do conſent and agree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues, as the cauſe efficient, and the effect. For God, being a iuſt iudge, pronounceth no man iuſt, neither acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth any, but him whome he hath firſt made iuſt.</p>
                  <p>And God maketh a man iuſt (whome he will pronounce iuſt) by imputation of iuſtice: that is, for ſo much as he imputeth iuſtice to him, or (that which is all one) imputeth not ſinnes vnto him, but pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth &amp; forgiueth them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 5.6.7.8.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt ſignification, the word <hi>[Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying]</hi> is taken <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. where the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>To him that worketh not, but belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in him that iustifieth the vngodly, his faith is imputed for iustice.</hi> Heere God is ſayd to iuſtifie the vngodly. But God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth not the vngodly iuſt, but maketh him iuſt; and that whiles he imputeth iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice vnto him: as the Apoſtle teacheth in this place. And then at laſt pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him iuſt. And ſo the Apoſtle himſelfe expoundeth the word <hi>Iustified,</hi> by <hi>to be made iuſt. Rom.</hi> 5.19.</p>
                  <p>In the latter ſignification it is taken <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33. where the Apoſtle ſayth: <hi>Who ſhall accuſe Gods elect? God is he that iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth. Who is hee that condemneth?</hi> Heere,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3055:6"/>vnto iuſtification is manifeſtly oppoſed condemnation: whereby we may perceiue that by that word here is ſignified iudicial acquitting, whereby the iudge pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth iuſt and innocent the guiltie partie, (that is, him that is accuſed and brought to the iudgement ſeate.)</p>
                  <p>But, Iuſtification being taken this latter way, is againe to be diſtinguiſhed. For it is done either in this life, and that in iuſtifying euery one apart by himſelfe and ſecretly: or after this life, in that vniuerſall day of iudgement, in altogether and openly.</p>
                  <p>For God hath ſet vp his iudgement ſeat in the conſcience of man, in as much as he hath ſo indued ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s mind with knowledge of iuſt and vniuſt, that if he haue done any vniuſt thing, his conſcience of it owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, as it were ſummoneth him to Gods iudgement ſeat, and accuſeth him: and if he be by others accuſed vniuſtly, his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience excuſeth him. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.20.21.</p>
                  <p>In this life therefore God iuſtifieth or pronounceth man iuſt, ſo far forth as he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth teſtimony to his ſoule (by the holy Ghoſt, the word of grace being the means) of imputed iuſtice, or of forgiuenes of ſins, and by conſequence, of adoption, for the ſatisfaction ſake of the mediator, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3055:7"/>
And in that day of iudgement, Chriſt being appointed of the father iudge of all, will with his mouth openly before all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men, pronounce iuſt, and crowne with life eternall the reward of iuſtice, all thoſe that before were iuſtified in this life, both by imputation of iuſtice, and by that ſecret teſtimonie of the holy Ghoſt. But the reſt he will condemne as tranſgreſſors of the law, and puniſh them with eternall paines, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12.13.14.15.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The ſtate of the controuerſie, and partition of this disputation.</head>
                  <p>FVrthermore, about mans Iuſtification before God, being taken the firſt way, this queſtion chiefly is controuerted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the profeſſors of the Goſpell, and the Papiſts, eſpecially the Ieſuites: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iuſtificaion be infuſing of iuſtice, or whether it be imputing of iuſtice? For the Papiſts ſay, that iuſtification is infuſing of iuſtice: but the Goſpellers ſay, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting of iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>We in the firſt place will declare and confirme the Goſpellers opinion as true,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3055:7"/>and therefore firſt by nature: then will we recite and refute the opinion of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Gospellers opinion expounded by ſeuen parts.</head>
                  <p>WHen the Goſpellers therefore ſay, that iuſtification is imputing of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, their meaning is, 1. that man by himſelf and his own nature vniuſt, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for iuſt: 2. and thereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced iuſt of God: 3. in as much as he forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him his ſinnes for the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, performed for him: 4. and apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him by faith: 5. and therfore that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is iuſtified by faith only: becauſe he is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iuſt, and by conſequence pronounced iuſt, for Chriſtes ſatisfaction only which is imputed to him by faith only: for that he doth not apprehend and apply it to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but by faith: 6. and ſo that man is iuſtified, partly by Gods grace or free loue, with which he being moued, did ordayne Chriſt to be ſatisfier or mediator for the elect: 7. partly by Gods iuſtice, whereby accepting Chriſts ſatisfaction for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, he imputeth the ſame vnto them: and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3055:8"/>thereupon receiueth them into fauour, and adopteth them for ſonnes and heyres of eternall life.</p>
                  <p>The Goſpellers opinion being thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, it followeth next that we confirme by teſtimonies of ſcripture all the parts thereof, and free it from the obiections of the Papiſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The firſt part of the opinion expounded is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and the ſame confirmation freed from <hi>Bellarmines</hi> exception.</head>
                  <p>ANd firſt, that man by himſelfe and of his owne nature being vniuſt, is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for iuſt, <hi>Paul</hi> beareth witneſſe <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.6. in theſe words, <hi>To him that worketh not, but beleeueth in him that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth the vngodly, his faith is imputed for iustice: as alſo</hi> Dauid <hi>declareth the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that man to whome God imputeth iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> The like ſentences are in the ſame chapter, <hi>verſe.</hi> 9.10.22.23.24.</p>
                  <p>Againſt this proofe <hi>Bellarmine</hi> excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Booke of iuſtification Chap. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> that the word <hi>Impute</hi> in this place <q>doth not ſignifie a bare accounting: but an accounting whereunto the truth in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3055:8"/>thing it ſelfe maketh anſwere, as is plaine by theſe words, <hi>To him that worketh, wages is imputed, not according to grace, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to debt.</hi> For it is certaine, that to him that worketh, wages is due, not only in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and accounting, but in truth and in deede.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Here <hi>Bellarmine</hi> firſt of all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth the fault of falſhood, in as much as he inuerteth the order of the Apoſtles words, that they may ſerue his purpoſe. For it is not in that place, <hi>To him that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, wages is imputed, not according to grace, &amp;c.</hi> But it is, <hi>To him that worketh, wages is not imputed according to grace, &amp;c.</hi> Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may <hi>Bellarmine</hi> except, that it skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not, whither way the aduerbe of denyall be there placed: becauſe, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be there placed, yet in the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, the word <hi>Imputed,</hi> is to be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thus: But (the wages) <hi>is imputed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to debt.</hi> For by the very phraſe wee may perceiue, that after the words <hi>[ou logizetai] is not imputed,</hi> theſe words muſt bee vnderſtoode <hi>[tout'estin ou dido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tai] that is, is not giuen:</hi> and therefore that in the oppoſition, the word <hi>[dido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tai] giuen,</hi> is to be vnderſtoode, that the whole ſentence is this: <hi>[to ergazomeno
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3055:9"/>ho misthos ou logízetai, toutéstin on di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotai cata chárin, alla dídotai cata tó opheí<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lema:]</hi> that is; <hi>To him that worketh, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is not imputed, that is to ſay, is not giuen according to grace: but is giuen according to debt.</hi> And if <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will not graunt this<note n="*" place="margin">i. want of a word.</note> 
                     <hi>ellipſis,</hi> he muſt confeſſe that here is a manifeſt<note n="†" place="margin">i. aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a word.</note> 
                     <hi>pleonaſmus</hi> in the former part, and alſo a manifeſt<note place="margin">i. abuſe of a word.</note> 
                     <hi>catachreſis</hi> in the latter part. For if one ſay, <hi>Wages is not imputed:</hi> is not this as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Wages is not giuen according to grace?</hi> It is therefore a <hi>pleonaſmus</hi> if one ſay, <hi>It is not imputed according to grace.</hi> Alſo if any ſay, <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is not imputed, but is giuen according to debt:</hi> he ſpeaketh properly. Therefore if one ſay, <hi>Wages is imputed according to debt:</hi> he (as touching the word <hi>imputed</hi>) ſpeaketh improperly. Wherefore this place is not of force to ſhift off the other: in which it is plaine by the Apoſtles words, that the proper ſignification of the word <hi>Imputed,</hi> is kept. For he ſayth, that <hi>Faith is imputed for iustice to him that worketh not, but beleeueth in him that iuſtifieth the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</hi> Which what other thing is it, then that man is iuſtified, not by debt or deſert of his works, but by grace for Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction apprehended by faith? It is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3055:9"/>therefore nothing to the matter that <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ſayth: that wages is ſo imputed, that in the meane time it is due indeed. As though it were in the ſame reſpect ſaid, that faith is imputed for <hi>Iustice.</hi> But euen <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe alſo tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that faith is giuen to man of grace, and likewiſe, that Iuſtification of which we ſpeake in this place: which he is wont to name the firſt. Whereupon doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it followeth, that neither faith nor this Iuſtification is owed to a man; ſeeing debt and grace are heere manifeſtly ſet one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an other.</p>
                  <p>And whereas <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, that by the word <hi>Imputing,</hi> is ſignified that accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting wherunto the truth in the thing it ſelfe maketh aunſwere: it is truly ſaid, if it be rightly vnderſtood. For to whom God imputeth iuſtice, they are truly iuſt; but by imputed iuſtice, and not inherent; as <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> vnderſtandeth. Euen as he whoſe debts his ſuretie hath paid to the creditor, oweth the creditor indeede nothing, though himſelfe paide not his debts, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had wherewith to pay them.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3055:10"/>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The confirmation and freeing of the ſecond part.</head>
                  <p>SEcondly, that man of himſelfe and his owne nature vniuſt, but now being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with imputed iuſtice, is pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Iuſt of God: the truth of this ſentence is plaine by theſe teſtimonies, in which condemnation is oppoſed to iuſtification: as <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Iudgement verily of one vnto condemnation: but grace of many offences vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iuſtification.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>As by the fall of one, ſinne entred vpon all men vnto condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſo alſo by the iuſt-worke</hi> (dicáioma) <hi>of one, iuſtice entred vpon all men vnto iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life.</hi> And Chap. 8.33.34. <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? It is God that iuſtifieth, who is he that condemneth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againſt this proofe <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth: that the word <hi>Iustification</hi> doth not alwaies pertain to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t place, becauſe it is oppoſed to condemnation. For condemnation is ſometime an effect of the fault which deſerueth puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And as <hi>Adam</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned vs, not by iudging, nor after the maner vſed in iudgement places,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3055:10"/>
                     <q>but by imprinting originall blame, but God hath conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned by iudging: ſo Chriſt as the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> iuſtifieth vs by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out our ſinnes, and infuſing grace: and ſecondly ſhal iuſtifie vs in the day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by declaring them iuſt whom he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath made iuſt.</q> I anſwer. Firſt this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maketh nothing againſt the proofe brought from <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. For althogh the word <hi>condemning</hi> be not alwaies belonging to the iudgement place; yet that it is ſo there, is manifeſt by that which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Who ſhall accuſe Gods elect?</hi> Moreouer this exception corrupteth the place of the 5. Chapter, both touching the words, &amp; tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſenſe. For the Apoſtle ſaith not there, either that <hi>Adam</hi> condemned vs, or Chriſt iuſtifieth vs: but ſaith, by one offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Adam,</hi> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that is, guiltineſſe came vpon all men vnto co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation: likewiſe by the iuſt-work <hi>(dicaloma)</hi> that is, ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, the gift, that is, iuſtice came vpon all men, vnto iuſtification of life. Where both conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation &amp; iuſtification are refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto god as Iudge: who may with right co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne all <hi>Adams</hi> natural childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the ſin that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted; &amp; who iuſtifieth them to whom he hath giuen iuſtice, for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction ſake of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3055:11"/>
Furthermore, <hi>Bellarmines</hi> reaſoning from a contrary ſenſe, or from a like reaſon of contraries, ſtayeth vpon a falſe ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: to wit, a falſe oppoſition of contraries. For theſe are not oppoſite one to an other, <hi>to imprint originall blame,</hi> and <hi>to put out ſins,</hi> (to wit, from nature) <hi>and infuſe grace,</hi> that is, inherent iuſtice. But theſe are oppoſite, <hi>to imprint originall blame,</hi> and, <hi>to put out ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall blame;</hi> likewiſe, <hi>to obtaine imputation of iuſtice.</hi> And indeed as <hi>Adam</hi> imprinted by his fall original blame in all his children, ſo Chriſt, for thoſe that pertaine vnto him, hath put out that blame, and obtained im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of iuſtice by his ſatiſfaction.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer, although as <hi>Adam</hi> did not onely imprint blame in his poſteritie, but alſo by generation infuſed into them the very force of ſinne: ſo Chriſt alſo, hath not onely put out the blame of the elect, and obtained imputation of iuſtice for them, but alſo regenerateth them by his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and by that regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, putteth out the force of ſinne, and infuſeth iuſtice or ſtudie of good workes: yet in that place of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, he ſpeaketh not of this benefite of Chriſt, but onely of the other. And of the benefit of regeneration or ſanctification, he entreateth afterwards in the 6.7. &amp;. 8. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3055:11"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The confirmation and clearing of the third part.</head>
                  <p>THirdly, that man is accounted for iuſt, and pronounced iuſt of God, in as much as God forgiueth him his ſins for the ſatiſfaction of Chriſt, and therefore that iuſtification is no other thing then forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: theſe ſayings teach vs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.7.8. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>That bleſſed is that man, to whom God imputeth iuſtice without works:</hi> ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiuen, and whoſe ſinnes are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered: bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord ſhall not impute ſinne,</hi> In theſe words it is certaine, that the full definition of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is contained: for of this the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle manifeſtly there entreateth: to wit, minding to teach how man is iuſtified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, as appeareth by comparing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither thoſe things which go before, from the 17. verſe of the 1. Chapter, vnto this place. And he defineth Iuſtification here, by imputation of iuſtice, or (that which he taketh for the ſame) for giueneſſe of ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>A gainſt this proofe, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3055:12"/>that <hi>Paul</hi> alleageth not this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Booke of iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Chap. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> perfectly to define Iuſtification: but onely to proue, that true Iuſtification is the gift of God, and cannot <q>be gotten by our owne ſtrength. He alſo ſaith, it may be anſwered, that in theſe words a perfect definition is contained, but intricately. For, forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, ſaith he, cannot be except iuſtice be infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: euen as darkneſſe is not driuen away, except light come in place therof. Alſo: by not imputing of ſins, ſaith he, the Apoſtle gathereth imputing of iuſtice: and by this teacheth, that theſe two cannot be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, forgiueneſſe of ſinnes and giuing of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to wit, inherent; for this <hi>Bellarmine</hi> vnderſtandeth.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I aunſwere, that <hi>Paul</hi> alleageth the teſtimonie of this Pſalme perfectly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine Iuſtification, is plaine by his drift, and comparing togither things that went before: as euen now we warned. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> feigneth here a falſe drift. Whereupon it followeth, that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo falſe, that heere is contained a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect definition intricately; to wit, infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of inherent iuſtice beeing vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode herewithall, as the other, and that the principall part of iuſtification.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:3055:12"/>
And although it be true, that with iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith, inherent iuſtice is togither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, not perfect, but begunne: yet is it not true, neither followeth it, that this iuſtice is a part of that iuſtice whereby wee ſtand before the iudgement ſeate of GOD, about which the Apoſtle dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in this place. Beſides, <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> maketh a falſe compariſon. For infuſion of iuſtice is not ſo in reſpect of forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, as infuſion of light into the ayre, to driue darkeneſſe out of the ſame: but is ſo compared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the reall putting out of inhabiting ſinne, which the ſcripture calleth mortification of the fleſh and of the olde man. For how much as inherent iuſtice is infuſed, that is, how much as the ſpirit or new man is quickned: ſo much is inhabiting ſinne put out, or the fleſh and olde man mortified. Moreouer, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> falſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreteth the Apoſtles reaſoning; as thogh he gathered imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of iuſtice, by not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting of ſinnes, as if it were ſome diuerſe thing. For the Apoſtle doth not gather here a diuerſe thing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a diuerſe: but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth imputation of iuſtice by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of <hi>Dauid:</hi> whereby appeareth, that hee holdeth <hi>imputation of Iuſtice</hi> (which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3055:13"/>he would prooue) and <hi>not imputing of ſinnes</hi> (which is mentioned in the teſtimonie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged) for one and the ſame thing. For otherwiſe he ſhould not proue his purpoſe. For it were ready to except: Thou art in hand to proue imputation of iuſtice: but <hi>Dauid</hi> mentioneth not imputation of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, but not imputing of ſinnes: but theſe are diuers. Wherefore by that teſtimonie, thou haſt yet proued nothing. Thus I ſay, might one except againſt the Apoſtles proofe. Laſtly, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> falſly expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth imputation of iuſtice, by giuing of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, in as much as he vnderſtandeth inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent iuſtice: ſeeing theſe be diuers: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any ſpeech of inherent iuſtice in this place: and finally, ſeeing it implieth a contradiction, for inherent iuſtice to be imputed.</p>
                  <p>But let vs bring now more teſtimonies to confirme the ſentence propoſed:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Proofe.</hi>
                     </note> viz. that man is iuſtified, in as much as his ſinnes are forgiuen him, for the ſatiſfaction of Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Whom</hi> (to wit Chriſt) <hi>God hath ſette foorth to bee a reconciliation through faith in his bloud, &amp;c. that he way be iuſt, and iuſtifying him that is of the faith of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> And Chapter 4.24.25. <hi>It ſhall hee imputed vnto vs</hi> (to wit, faith for iuſtice)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3055:13"/>
                     <hi>which beleeue in him that raiſed vp Ieſus our Lord from the dead, who was deliuered to death for our faults, and raiſed vp for our iuſtification.</hi> And Chapter, 5.9. <hi>Iuſtified by his bloud.</hi> And Chap. 10.6.7. <hi>The iuſtice which is of faith,</hi> ſaith thus: <hi>Say not in thy heart, who ſhall goe vp to heauen? this is to bring Chriſt from on high:</hi> or, <hi>who ſhall goe downe into the deepe? this is to bring Christ againe from the dead. Gal.</hi> 2.20.21. <hi>I liue by faith of the ſon of God, who loued mee, and gaue himſelfe for me: I doo not abrogate the grace of God: for if iuſtice be by the law, then Chriſt died in vaine. Ephe.</hi> 1.6.7. <hi>God by his grace hath made vs gracious in that belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued one, in whom we haue redemption by his bloud, euen forgiueneſſe of ſinnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againſt theſe proofes ſome may except, that in theſe ſpeeches mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of Chriſts ſatisfaction, as of the firſt mouing and deſeruing cauſe, for which man is iuſtified, and his ſins forgiuen him: but hence it followeth not that Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth only in forgiuenes of ſins: becauſe that Chriſt by his ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath deſerued and obtained of God for vs, not onely forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, but alſo the gift of the holy Ghoſt, which doth rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate vs, and infuſe iuſtice into vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3055:14"/>
I anſwere. That which is heere ſaide of Chriſts merits, is indeed true: but yet in thoſe ſpeeches, is no ſpeech of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but onely of forgiueneſſe of ſins as the effect of Chriſts ſatisfaction, and as the thing by which we are formally iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: as chiefly appeareth by that place, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.6.7. Wherfore we muſt determin, that it is one and the ſame thing with the Apoſtle, for <hi>A man to be iuſtified by the bloud of Christ;</hi> and <hi>A man to haue his ſinnes forgiuen for the bloud of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let vs adde alſo an other place,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Profe.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13.38.39. <hi>By this man</hi> (to wit Chriſt) <hi>is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to you forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: and from all things from which ye could not be uiſtisfied by Moſes law: by this man, euery one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth is iustified.</hi> Heere <hi>Iuſtification</hi> is manifeſtly defined, by forgiueneſſe of ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> excepteth:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Booke of iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Chap. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> He that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, <q>to wit, as he ought: that is, by fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all things which faith ſheweth ſhould be fulfilled. For he that beleeueth a Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, though a moſt skilfull one, and that infallibly cureth, is not healed, except he receiue the medicines that hee appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3055:14"/>
I anſwere. This is a Ieſutiſh gloſſe, confounding things diuerſe, that I ſay not aduerſe: to wit, <hi>to beleeue in Christ;</hi> and, <hi>to fulfill the law;</hi> or doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe knitting a falſe conſequence, as though the fulfilling of the lawe becauſe it is ioyned with true faith, concurreth as a cauſe with the ſame to iuſtification. Moreouer, hee deceiueth by the diuerſe ſignification of the word <hi>beleeue:</hi> as though <hi>to beleeue in Chriſt,</hi> were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, then <hi>to beleeue Chriſt, that he is a moſt ſkilfull Phiſitian of ſoules, and curing infallibly, and in the meane time not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the medicines that hee appointeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I ſay, that to beleeue in Chriſt, is by faith to receiue and apply to ones ſelfe the medicines that Chriſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, namely his bloud ſhead for vs on the Croſſe, with feeling of the wrath of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> addeth: though the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <q>in this place nameth onely the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſins, yet is it no let, but iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation may be vnderſtood to conſiſt in forgiueneſſe of ſins, &amp; infuſion of iuſtice, For, forgiueneſſe of ſins is not only forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but is the waſhing away &amp; cleanſing of the fault: which wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3055:15"/>and cleanſing is not, except there ſucceed the brightneſſe of grace &amp; come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of iuſtice.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. That the Apoſtle in this place defineth Iuſtification by forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſins onely, is manifeſt, partly by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence of ſentences, wherof one is added to an other, as explaining the ſame: partly by the very phraſe, <hi>to be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſins:</hi> which is no other thing, then <hi>to be abſolued from ſins committed,</hi> &amp; by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, <hi>to obtaine forgiueneſſe of ſinnes.</hi> Moreouer, it is vnfitly diſtinguiſhed by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> as things diuerſe and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble one from an other, <hi>Forgiueneſſe of the puniſhment,</hi> and, <hi>cleanſing of the fault:</hi> when as cleanſing or rather forgiuing of the fault, is no other thing then deliuerance from the puniſhment: for hee is ſaid to forgiue the fault, that will not inflict de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued puniſhment for the fault. Beſides, hee confoundeth <hi>cleanſing of the fault, with cleanſing of inhabiting ſinne,</hi> which is by regeneration: ſeeing vnto the cleanſing of the fault, he oppoſeth the brightneſſe of grace and comelineſſe or ſeemelineſſe of iuſtice to wit, inherent.</p>
                  <p>Finally, he hideth a falſe conſequence, in that he ſaith; <hi>The cleanſing of the fault is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3055:15"/>not, except there ſucceed the brightneſſe of grace and comelineſſe of iustice.</hi> By which words hee inſinuateth, if iuſtification conſiſt in forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: and this is the cleanſing of the fault: and this cleanſing is not, except there ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede inherent iuſtice: it followeth, that inherent iuſtice alſo is part of that iuſtice wherwith man is formally iuſtified. But it is not neceſſarie, that inherent iuſtice ſhould be part of that iuſtice wherewith man is iuſtified, although that iuſtice wherewith man is iuſtified, befall no man (that is growen to yeares of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) without the gift of inherent iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> further excepteth,<q> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, ſaith he, in this place mention onely ſhould be made of iuſtifying from ſinne: yet in many other places, mention is made of ſanctification, cleanſing, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, renewing and the like, which ſhew the other part of Iuſtification.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I aunſwere. It ſeemeth, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> by the very phraſe of this place, <hi>to be iustified from things,</hi> vnderſtood, that ſpeech heere properly was of iuſtification from ſinnes: that is, of forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: but leaſt he ſhould hurt his cauſe, he will not freely confeſſe this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3055:16"/>
Then, in that hee ſaith, mention is made in other places of ſanctification or renewing, it maketh nothing to the matter. For there is indeed mention made thereof euery where: but not as part of iuſtification, as heere <hi>Bellarmine</hi> by beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the queſtion doth affirme.</p>
                  <p>Yet <hi>Bellarmine</hi> proceedeth in his exception. That <hi>from which ye could not be iuſtified in the law of Moſes,</hi> ſignifieth, ſaith he, that the obſeruation of the law, preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on by our owne ſtrength, or by the help of the law only doth not iuſtifie: not that the true obſeruation of the law is not iuſtice; but that the law cannot bee kept, before forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. For when God by Chriſts merits reconcileth any, he togither, both forgiueth him his ſinnes, and infuſeth charitie, by which he keepeth the commandements of the law.</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Whatſoeuer that ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>To be iuſtified in the law of Moſes:</hi> the Apoſtle ſaith clearely, that the Iewes to whom he ſpeaketh, could not be iuſtified in <hi>Moſes</hi> law: which thing alſo <hi>Peter</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth of the fathers, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. where he ſaith, <hi>that the law was a yoake, that neither they nor their fathers could beare.</hi> And who skilfull in the holy ſtorie, knoweth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3055:16"/>not, that there were among the fathers ſome godly, and therefore endued with forgiueneſſe of ſinnes and the gift of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation? And yet they, as <hi>Peter</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, could not beare the yoake of the law, that is, by keeping of the law, be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified from their ſinnes. Alſo who dare affirme, that none of thoſe Iewes whom <hi>Paul</hi> then ſpake vnto, was endued with true faith in Chriſt to come, although as yet they knew not who he was: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were alſo endued with the gift of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration? Surely that ſome of them were ſuch, may be gathered from the 43. verſe, where it is ſaid, that many of thoſe Iewes and religious proſelytes followed <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas:</hi> and that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded them to continue in the grace of God. And yet theſe, as <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, could not in the law, that is, by the law be iuſtified. Wherefore that which <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ſaith, that the true keeping of the lawe is iuſtice, is true: but it is not true which hee vnderſtandeth and inſinuateth in the wordes following, namely, that they which haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of GOD, forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and the gift of charitie, can performe the true, (that is, perfect) obſeruation
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3055:17"/>of the lawe; ſo that by that iuſtice of the law, they can ſtand in the iudgement of God.</p>
                  <p>An other place for a ſentence there is,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>4.</hi> Proofe.</note> 
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. where the Publican is ſaid to bee iuſtified, when onely hee had asked forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, ſaying, <hi>O God bee mercifull vnto mee a ſinner.</hi> Contrariwiſe, the <hi>Phariſee</hi> preaching the gifts of God beſtowed on him, and giuing thankes, went away not iuſtified. Therefore Iuſtification conſiſteth not in gifts and good workes, though done through Gods helpe, but onely in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">In the place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cited.</note>Againſt this proofe <hi>Bellarmine</hi>excepteth thus: <q>when the Publican ſaid, O God bee mercifull to mee a ſinner, hee asked not onely forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the debt, as though hee would bee vnrighteous, yet not ſo accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of GOD, nor puniſhed: but hee asked whole reconciliation; and the ſame hee obtained. Whereupon, our Lorde concludeth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>: This man went away iuſtified from him, for euery one that humbleth himſelfe, ſhall be exalted: and hee that exalteth himſelfe, ſhall be humbled.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3055:17"/>The exaltation of the humble and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent publican, ſignifieth doubtleſſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more then onely forgiuenes of his offence. For they are not ſaid to be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whoſe debts are forgiuen: but which are aduanced vnto degrees and honours. Therefore the publican is for this ſaid to be exalted, becauſe of a ſinner he was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly made iuſt; of the ſeruant of ſinne, the ſeruant of iuſtice; of the child of the diuell, the child of God. Moreouer, the Phariſee, deſerued to be ſet after the Publican, not becauſe he rehearſed the gifts of God, and gaue the Lord thanks: but becauſe he was full of the ſwelling of pride, and truſted in his owne iuſtice, ſo as that he would not craue any thing to beadded to him, nothing to be forgiuen him: beſides alſo hee contemned the humble Publican.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth heere croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly cauill at the ſentence of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Goſpell, as if they did teach that ſuch ſhal receiue forgiueneſſe of ſins, as will yet be vnrighteous: or as if ſuch a purpoſe can ſtand with carneſt ſuite for remiſſion of ſinnes. And where he ſaith, that the Publican when he ſaid, <hi>God be mercifull vnto me a ſinner,</hi> asked not onely
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3055:18"/>forgiueneſſe of his debt: what is this but to wreſt cleare words from their ſimple ſenſe? Alſo, what meaneth this, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> oppoſeth whole reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto forgiueneſſe of debt? As though that forgiuing of debt, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, were not a whole, but onely a halfe reconciliation, againſt the manifeſt teſtimonies of ſcripture: <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9.10. <hi>Beeing instified by his bloud, wee ſhall be ſaued now much more by him from wrath; for if when we were enemies, wee were reconciled to God by the death of his ſonne: much more beeing reconciled, wee ſhall be ſaued by his life. Heere it is</hi> manifeſt, that <hi>to be reconciled vnto God,</hi> is the ſame that <hi>to be iustified of God,</hi> as may be perceiued by Chap. 4. ver. 5.6.7. Yet there is a clearer place, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>God was in Christ reconciling the world to himſelfe, not imputing to them their ſinnes.</hi> Behold whether the Apoſtle dooth not expreſly define reconciliation wherewith we are reconciled vnto God, by forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes? And whereas <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> interpreteth that clauſe, <hi>Euery one that humbleth himſelfe, &amp;c.</hi> ſo as if the Lord would define what it is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified: hee miſſeth the marke: for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3055:18"/>the Lord had no other purpoſe, then by that prouerbiall ſentence, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that ſpeciall two-folde example, the one of a man iuſtified, the other of a man not obtaining Iuſtification. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, where he interpreteth <hi>to be exalted,</hi> of infuſion of iuſtice, he vſeth a fallacie of the conſequent, reaſoning from the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to the ſpeciall, affirmatiuely, thus; <hi>To be inſtified is to be exalted: therefore it is, to bee exalted by infuſion of inherent iuſtice.</hi> But though it be true, that hee which is iuſtified, is exalted not onely by adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo by regeneration: yet hence it followeth not, that <hi>Iuſtification</hi> is the ſame that regeneration. Moreouer, <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> in this place contradicteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, whiles now he granteth, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinne is ſignified by exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſtraight way denieth that they are ſayd to be exalted whoſe debts are forgiuen.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, as touching the Phariſee: it is true, that for ſpirituall pride and truſt in his owne iuſtice, he was repulſed from God: but in the meane time, this alſo is true, that the Lord would teach by this example, that this pride is an vnſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable companion of that deſire whereby
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3055:19"/>men ſeeke iuſtice in their owne workes. Neither is <hi>Zacheus, Luk.</hi> 19. (which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample <hi>Bellarmine</hi> obiecteth) ſayd to be iuſtified by good workes: although when he promiſed good works, the Lord ſayd vnto him, <hi>To day is ſaluation come to this houſe:</hi> but only the ſinceritie of his faith is after this manner commended by the effects. And the cauſe of <hi>Zacheus</hi> ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is ſhewed in the words immediatly following; for he ſayth, <hi>To day is ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion come to this houſe, for that he alſo is the ſonne of</hi> Abraham: to wit, infiſting in the ſteps of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, as <hi>Paul</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this ſonne-ſhip, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12. For as touching the fleſh, many were <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſonnes, to whome notwithſtanding ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation came not. And king <hi>Ezechias,</hi> (which example <hi>Bellarmine</hi> addeth) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſhewed his good works with a ſincere hart: yet he thought not, that he was by them iuſt before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of God: like as <hi>Paule</hi> ſayd, <hi>I know nothing by my ſelfe; but I am not hereby iustified.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3055:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The confirmation of the fourth part.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FOurthly, that man is iuſtified by faith, in as much as by faith he layeth hold on, and applieth to himſelfe Chriſtes ſatisfaction, may be perceiued by theſe ſayings,</hi> Rom. <hi>3.24.25.</hi> They are iustified by the redemption made in Chriſt, whome God hath ſet forth to be a reconciliation through faith in his bloud. <hi>And chap. 4.24.25.</hi> It ſhal be imputed to vs <hi>(to wit, faith for iuſtice)</hi> which beleeue in him that raiſed vp our Lord Ieſus from the dead: which was deliuered to death for our faults, and raiſed vp for our iustification. <hi>And chap. 10.6.7.</hi> The iuſtice which is of faith, ſaith thus. Say not in thy hart, who ſhall go vp into heauen? this is to bring Chriſt from aboue. Or, who ſhall go downe into the deepe? this is to bring Chriſt againe from the dead. Gal. <hi>2.20.</hi> I liue by faith of the ſonne of God, who loued me, and gaue himſelfe for me, &amp;c. Rom. <hi>4.5.</hi> To him that worketh not, but beleeneth in him that iuſtifieth the vngodly, his faith is imputed for iuſtice. <hi>Where it is manifeſt, that by the name faith, by a</hi> metonymie
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3055:20"/>
                     <hi>of the adioynt, is to be vnderſtood any thing which is by faith imputed to a man for iuſtice. For to ſpeake properly, that which is in a man, is not ſaid to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, but that which is without a man. And faith is in a man, but Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction which faith apprehendeth is without a man: whereby it cometh to paſſe, that it is imputed vnto man by faith: that is to ſay, is accounted his, ſo as man is eſteemed in this place, as if he had perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the ſatisfaction for himſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The confirmation and clearing of the fift part.</head>
                  <p>FIftly, that man is iuſtified by faith on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that is, for the onely ſatiſfaction of Chriſt apprehended by faith: and not partly by faith, that is, for Chriſts ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion imputed; and partly by works, that is, for inherent iuſtice: may be gathered by the ſayings following, which teach that a man is iuſtified without workes. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Where is then the reioycing? It is excluded. By what law? of workes? no; but by the law of faith.</hi> And by and by,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3055:20"/>verſe, 28. <hi>We conclude therfore, that a man is iuſtified by faith without the workes of the law.</hi> And Chap. 4.2. <hi>If Abraham our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were iuſtified by workes, he hath where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to reioyce, but not with God.</hi> Gal. 2.16. <hi>Knowing that man is not iuſtified by the workes of the law, but by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt: we alſo haue beleeued in Ieſus Chriſt, that wee might bee iustified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the law.</hi> Eph. 2.8.9. <hi>By grace ye are ſaued through faith, not of workes.</hi> Tit. 3.5. <hi>Not of iuſt workes which we had done, but of his owne mercie he ſaued vs, &amp;c.</hi> Phil. 3.9. <hi>That I may be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in him, not hauing my own iuſtice which is of the lawe, but that which is by faith of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vnto thoſe ſayings wherein works are oppoſed to faith,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>I.</hi> Booke of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Chap. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> excepteth <q>firſt in generall or in commune, that by works which are oppoſed to faith, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from Iuſtification, are vnderſtood works which go before faith, &amp; which are done by the only ſtrength of free-will, &amp; not all abſolutely. And this he ſaith may be proued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. where we read, ſaith he, to him that worketh, wages is imputed as by debt, not as by grace. In which place the Apoſtle openeth himſelfe, ſaith he, what ſhuld be vnderſtood by workes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3055:21"/>which are oppoſed to faith: and ſaith, that he calleth them works, to which that which is giuen is wages, not grace. And ſuch be not any, but thoſe that are done by the onely ſtrength of freewill. For that which is giuen to the works that be done of grace, ſuch as is the very act of faith, and thoſe that follow thereupon, is not ſimply wages, but alſo grace: yea more grace then wages. </q>Thus ſaith <hi>Bellarmine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. It is falſe, that <hi>Pault</hi> ſhould here ſay, he calleth them works, to which that which is giuen is wages, not grace: that is, which are done by the onely ſtrength of freewill. For, that he ſpeaketh of works in generall, whether they be done by the ſtrength of freewill or by grace, appeareth by this, that he intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth there of <hi>Abrahams</hi> workes, thoſe which he had done of grace and faith, as that he was obedient to Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and truſting vpon his promiſe, left his countrie of <hi>Chaldea,</hi> and went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a land which God was to ſhew him: alſo, that he refuſed not to offer his onely ſonne <hi>Iſaak</hi> at Gods commandement: for theſe are thoſe workes wherein he might reioyce and boaſt with men. And from theſe works doth <hi>Pault</hi> derogate
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3055:21"/>Iuſtification before God, by this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is taken from the generall; for that to him that worketh, wages is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as by debt, and is not imputed, that is, not giuen of grace: but to <hi>Abraham</hi> iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice was imputed. And whereas <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> faith: that which is giuen to workes which be done of grace, is partly wages, parly grace: therein hee feigneth, that things immediately aduerſe, may ſtand togither; and that againſt the Apoſtles manifeſt ſentence, both in this place, where he oppoſeth grace to debt, and by conſequence, to wages, as that cannot ſtand togither; and alſo Chap. 11.6. where he ſaith, <hi>If by grace</hi> (to wit, there be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of certaine Iewes that are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) <hi>it is not now of workes,</hi> (that is, deſerts of workes) <hi>otherwiſe were no more grace. But if of workes: then not now of grace: otherwiſe workes were no more workes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hauing firſt ſet downe that generall anſwere,<note place="margin">Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that place. Ro. <hi>3 27.</hi>
                     </note> maketh anſwere afterward vnto euery of thoſe ſayings. And firſt vnto that place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. he anſwereth, that the reioycing of the Iewes is excluded by the law of of faith, <q>not by the law of deeds: becauſe man is iuſtified of grace, which firſt of all inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3055:22"/>faith, then by faith, leadeth vnto mercie and good works: and is not iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the law of deeds, that is by the only knowledge of the law, &amp; ſtrength of free will.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer. Although Gods grace wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man is iuſtified, leadeth him by faith vnto good works: yet is not in that reſpect man ſaid to be juſtified by faith (as <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> inſinuateth) becauſe of faith he doth good workes, but he is ſaid to be iuſtified by faith, becauſe by faith he leyeth holde on Chriſts ſatisfaction, for which only he is iuſtified. Moreouer, it is falſe, that the Apoſtle vnderſtandeth thoſe workes only which are done according to Gods law, by the ſtrength of free will. For it is plain by <hi>Abrahams</hi> exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently addeth to this ſentence, by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſis in the beginning of the chapter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, that he ſpeaketh of thoſe workes that are done of grace and faith.</p>
                  <p>Againſt this anſwere, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth:<q> that the Apoſtle ſaith not, where is the reioycing? but, where is the reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing? that is, where is the reioycing, wherewith thou reioyceſt in thy ſelfe and not in the Lord? And of workes done of faith, and thereby of grace; ſeeing faith
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3055:22"/>is of grace; none can reioyce but in the Lord. Which reioycing is not forbidden, ſeeing the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, Hee that reioyceth, let him reioyce in the Lord.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. That Pronowne, <hi>thy,</hi> is not in the Greeke. Neuertheleſſe, by the very matter it appeareth, that it muſt be vnderſtood. Then, that there is no need the Pronowne ſhould be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth; for reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing is rightly ſaid to be his that reioiceth; whether he reioyce in himſelf, or in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Laſtly (that which is chiefly to be marked) the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing wherewith any may truly reioyce, that he is iuſt by inherent iuſtice, bred of perfect obſeruation of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements of the law, whether he performe this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of naturall ſtrength, or of Gods ſingular grace. And ſuch reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing no man hath: becauſe all haue tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the law, and they which begin to obſerue it by Gods ſingular grace, yet can they not (in this life) obſerue it perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo as for that obſeruation they can be counted iuſt of God. In the meane while it is true, that it is lawfull for the godly to reioyce in the Lord: but ſo farre forth as they reioyce not falſly: and they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3055:23"/>ſhould falſly reioyce, if they ſhould ſay, that they can by Gods grace perfectly fulfill the law, ſo as by fulfilling thereof, they may be iuſt before God.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond place from <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Wee gather that a man is iustified by faith without the workes of the law:</hi> Bellarmine paſſeth ouer in ſilence, and anſwereth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to it in ſpeciall. But in the ſecond place he anſwereth vnto that ſaying, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.2. of <hi>Abraham:</hi> and withall, vnto the reſt of the places before recited. He ſaith therefore,<note place="margin">Exception againſt the other places before recited.</note> that <hi>Abraham</hi> was iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith, not by workes that went before faith. And the ſame he anſwereth <q>vnto the places following, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. for in all thoſe places, are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded onely workes done before faith.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. The Apoſtle derogateth Iuſtification not onely from thoſe works which are done before faith, but alſo from thoſe which are done after faith. For he ſpeaketh of <hi>Abrahams</hi> workes, which are mentioned in ſcripture for to ſhew his vprightneſſe, as, that he obeyed God, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of his owne countrey, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his ſonne. But the workes which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did before faith, are mentioned in the ſcripture, not as ſuch whereof hee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3055:23"/>might reioyce, but as ſuch whereof hee might worthily be aſhamed: namely, that he ſerued ſtrange gods, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 24.2. Alſo in <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. hee ſpeaketh in generall of the workes of the law, wherein the Iewes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed themſelues, among whom were many regenerate, and endued with faith of Chriſt, as cannot be denied: although they knew not, that that Ieſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> was the Chriſt, and that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhould be imputed to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him. Beſides in this ſaying. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. is to be noted the want of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding particle [<hi>tout'ésti,</hi> 1. <hi>that is:</hi>] which being obſerued, it will be euident, that heere are contained excluſiue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, equiualent to that excluſiue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle <hi>[onely.]</hi> For it is, as if he ſhould ſay; <hi>Knowing that a man is not iuſtified by the workes of the law:</hi> that is, <hi>but by the faith of Ieſus Christ, &amp;c.</hi> And theſe are equiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, <hi>Not to be iuſtified but by faith,</hi> and <hi>to be iuſtified by faith onely.</hi> Beſides, although <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. and <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. hee taketh away iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication from workes done before faith, yet by this hee dooth not aſcribe it to workes done after faith.</p>
                  <p>Againſt this anſwere <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth, that the Apoſtle when hee ſaith,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3055:24"/>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Abraham</hi> was iuſtified by faith, not by workes; doth not reiect the workes done by faith, but affirmeth them not to bee don without faith: for if they had bin ſuch, they had neuer iuſtified him, therefore he excludeth (ſaith he) the workes which <hi>Abraham</hi> could haue done, not of faith.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But what is to mingle darkneſſe with the cleare light, if this be not? The Apoſtle openly denieth that <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> was iuſtified with God by works: &amp; ſpeaketh of works don by faith, as we haue now twiſe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and yet <hi>Bellarmine</hi> dareth to ſay, that the Apoſtle reiecteth not (to wit, from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) works done of faith. Then what meaneth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> when he ſaith, the Apoſtle affirmeth that <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> works were not done without faith: for if they had bin ſuch, they had neuer iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. But where doth the Apoſtle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this? And doth not now <hi>Bellarmine</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradict himſelfe: which affirmeth here, that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of <hi>Abrahams</hi> works done of faith: when yet before hee ſaid, in al thoſe places, ſpeech was of works done before faith? Alſo, dooth hee not ſtraightway in the words following again co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradict himſelfe, when he ſaith, that the Apoſtle excludeth works which <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3055:24"/>could haue done, not of faith?</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Beſides, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh with conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, namely thus: If <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> iuſtified by works not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grace of faith: ſurely he had reioycing, but not with god. And becauſe it is manifeſt inough (ſaith he) that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had reioycing alſo with god, therup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Apoſtle gathereth, that he was not iuſtified by works without faith, but by faith wherof good workes truly proceed.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> peruerteth the meaning of the Apoſtles words, in feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto him ſuch a ſyllogiſme: ye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly contradicteth the Apoſtles words. For the Apoſtle denieth that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had reioycing with God: but <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> affirmeth it. And that <hi>Bellarmines</hi> ſyllogiſme is feigned, appeareth by cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of ſencences. For when the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle had recited the obiection of the Iewes drawne from <hi>Abrahams</hi> exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as if hee had obtained the praiſe of iuſtice by woorkes: hee anſwereth by diſtinction: graunting that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> got that praiſe with men but not with God. Then, if in this place there were an hypotheticall or connex ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme, it ſhoulde bee ſuch as this:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3055:25"/>If <hi>Abraham</hi> were iuſtified by workes, he hath wherof to reioyce with God. But he hath not whereof to reioyce with God. Therefore hee was not iuſtified by workes.</p>
                  <p>The aſſumption of which ſyllogiſme, plainely contradicteth the aſſumption of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> ſyllogiſme: and the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is diuerſe from the concluſion of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> ſyllogiſme; becauſe it ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of workes in generall, when <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> ſpeaketh onely of works done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith.</p>
                  <p>Vnto the laſt place,<note place="margin">Exception againſt the place, Phil. <hi>3.9.</hi>
                     </note> from <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> anſwereth: that thoſe workes are called the iuſtice of the law, which are done through knowledge of the law, by the onely ſtrength of nature.</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. By that which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſignifieth, that hee truſted not in the iuſtice of workes which hee had done by the onely ſtrength of nature, it cannot firmely be gathered, that he truſted in the juſtice of workes which hee had done of faith. Yea he openly ſignifieth, that hee truſted in the onely iuſtice of faith. And this is the iuſtice which is imputed to man by faith, as he teacheth <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.6. and not the iuſtice of workes done of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3055:25"/>faith, inherent in a man. And in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place ſpeaking of this inherent iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, he ſaith, <hi>I know nothing by my ſelfe: but I am not hereby iuſtified.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The confirmation and clearing of the ſixt part.</head>
                  <p>HItherto of the fifth part of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence propoſed: now followeth of the ſixt, that man is iuſtified by the grace or free loue of God; in as much as God hath of fauour to man, ordained Chriſt for a Mediator or ſatisfactor: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe ſayings. <hi>Act:</hi> 15.11. <hi>By the grace of our Lord Ieſus Christ, wee beleeue that we ſhall be ſaued euen as they. Rom.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Are iuſtified freely by his grace, by the redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made in Ieſus Chriſt. Rom.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Therefore the inheritance is of faith, that it may be by grace: Rom.</hi> 5.15. <hi>If by the fal of that one, many are dead, much more the grace of God, and the gift by grace, which is by one man Ieſus Chriſt, hath abounded vnto many. And verſe.</hi> 17. <hi>they which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the abundance of grace, and the gift of iuſtice ſhall raigne in life through one, that is,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3055:26"/>Ieſus Christ.</hi> And verſ. 21. <hi>So grace might reigne by iustice vnto-eternall life, through Ieſus Christ our Lord.</hi> Rom. 11.5. <hi>Euen ſo at this preſent time there is a remnant accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the election of grace.</hi> Gal. 2.21. <hi>I do not abrogate the grace of God. For if iustice be by the law, then Christ died in vaine.</hi> Gal. 5.4. <hi>Yee are aboliſhed from Grist whoſoeuer are iuſtified by the Law, ye are fallen from grace.</hi> Eph. 1.5.6.7. <hi>Who hath predeſtinate vs to be adopted throgh Ieſus Chriſt, vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, according to the good pleaſure of his wilt to the praiſe of the glorie of his grace: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath made vs accepted in his beloued: by whom wee haue redemption through his bloud, &amp;c.</hi> Eph. 2.8. <hi>By grace ye are ſaued, &amp;c.</hi> Tit. 3.7. <hi>That wee beeing iuſtified by his grace, ſhould bee made heires according to the hope of eternall life.</hi> In all theſe ſpeeches, the word <hi>Grace,</hi> ſignifieth the fauour of God, wherewith he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth his elect.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Booke of iustifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Chap. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againſt this, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> excepteth: <q>that iuſtifying grace is not onely the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God, but a gift inherent in the minde, as may bee vnderſtood (ſaith he) by the diuerſe attributes and names thereof. For it is called the gift which wee receiue, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17. <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3055:26"/>the abundance of the grace and gift.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is ſaid, <hi>to be giuen by Chriſt. Grace and truth is made by Ieſus Christ. Ioh.</hi> 1. Now it is not rightly ſaid, that the good wil of God the Father is made by Chriſt. Alſo it is ſaid to be giuen of Chriſt by meaſure: <hi>To euery one of vs is giuen grace, according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt. Eph:</hi> 4. But the good will of God is not, giuen by meaſure, neither of Chriſt. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, it is compared to the <hi>being</hi> which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by creation. For therof we are ſaid to be <hi>Created in Chriſt, Eph.</hi> 2. &amp;, <hi>a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Gal.</hi> 5. But that whereby we are ſaid to be creatures, is inward and inherent. Finally, it is compared to the light, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>What part hath iustice with iniquitie? What fellowſhip hath light with darkneſſe?</hi> Eph. 5. <hi>Ye were ſometimes darkneſſe, but now are light in the Lord.</hi> 1. Ioh. 2. <hi>He that ſaith he is in the light and hateth his brother, is in darkneſſe.</hi> But certes light ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not a lucide body, except it be inherent, neither ſuffereth darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with it. Beſides, the grace by which the Apoſtle ſayth wee are iuſtified, is called alſo, <hi>loue ſhead in our hearts by the holy Ghoſt. Rom.</hi> 5. Alſo, by iuſtifying grace, wee are ſaide to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3055:27"/>liue. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>the ſpirit liueth for iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> But wee cannot bee rightly ſaide to liue by the outward fauour of God: when nothing is more inward then life is.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17. <hi>the grace</hi> and <hi>the gift,</hi> of iuſtice are openly diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: therefore the gift is not there cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the grace, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith. Then, there is there no ſpeech of inherent iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would: but of the iuſtice which God giueth, &amp; of the grace or fauour hee imputeth: for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh of the ſame iuſtice that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6. where he ſaid, iuſtice was imputed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. The name of <hi>Grace</hi> ſignifieth the benefite of redemption, by a <hi>metony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> of the cauſe efficient: but thereof it followeth not, that it is taken after the ſame maner in the ſayings rehearſed. As neither from the ſaying, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. where the name <hi>Grace,</hi> ſignifieth ſome ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all gift, profitable for the edifying of the Church. Neither yet by the other ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. where the name of <hi>Grace</hi> is not found; neither is the ſpeech of iuſtification, but of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And in that ſaying, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3055:27"/>
                     <hi>Loue is ſhead, &amp;c,</hi> is not meant the loue which is inherent, in vs, and wherewith wee loue God; but wherewith God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs: as is plaine by comparing it with the 8. verſe, where it is ſaid, <hi>God commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his loue towards vs, &amp;c.</hi> Finally, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10. hee ſpeaketh not of iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but of ſanctification, neither is there the name <hi>Iuſtification</hi> as <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> falſly alleageth; but the name of <hi>Iustice,</hi> whereby is there meant, a iuſt and holy life: as may appeare by the whole context and ſcope of that place: and not that iuſtice whereby a man ſtandeth before the iudgement ſeate of GOD; the diſputation of which matter, the Apoſtle finiſhed in the end of the ſift Chapter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The confirmation of the ſeuenth part.</head>
                  <p>THere remaineth the ſeuenth part of the ſentence propounded, to wit, that man is iuſtified by the iuſtice of God, whereby he accepteth Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for the elect. Of this <hi>Paule</hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:3055:28"/>teſtifieth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25.26. Where he ſaith, <hi>Whom</hi> (to wit Chriſt) <hi>God hath ſet forth to be are conciliation through faith in his bloud to declare his iustice, by the forgiueneſſe of the ſinnes, that are past through the patience of God, to ſhew at this time his iustice, that he might be iuſt and a iustifier of him which is of the faith of Ieſus.</hi> By which words the Apoſtle teacheth, that God declareth his iuſtice, in as much as he forgiueth ſinnes to them for whom Chriſt hath ſatisfied, namely the beleeuers. For it is the part of iuſtice, to be content, if ſatisfaction bee made for the debt by a ſuretie, and not to exact ſatiſfaction of the debter himſelfe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3055:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE SECOND Booke of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> VVherein the opinion of the Papists, and proofes of the ſame, are recited out of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> Booke, and refuted.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Papiſts opinion recited: which conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of foure parts.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto hath bene the firſt part of our ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded diſputation, the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Goſpell, touching <hi>Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> the other part fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, to wit, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the Papiſts.</p>
                  <p>The Papiſts opinion and ſentence therefore, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> deliuereth in theſe words, (2. Booke of <hi>Iustification,</hi> Chapter 2.) that Iuſtification is the infuſion of inherent iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3055:29"/>
                     <q>Alſo (in the ſame booke, Chap. 3.) that it is a regeneration and renewing through the goodneſſe of God, made in vs by the lauer of Baptiſme and ſheading out of the holy Ghoſt. Inherent iuſtice he maketh to conſiſt in faith, hope and charitie: (in the ſame booke, Chap. 2.) yet in an other place (1. booke of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> Chap. 2.) in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie onely. Therefore (in the ſame booke Chap. 13. and 2. booke. Chap. 4.) that faith iuſtifieth, not onely, but as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and firſt roote of Iuſtification. Alſo (2. booke of Iuſtification. Chap. 6.) that iuſtification conſiſteth not in onely forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. Finally, (in the ſame booke, Chap. 7.) that Iuſtification conſiſteth not in imputation of Chriſtes iuſtice. All which things how he ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth to proue, let vs ſee after.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The profe of the firſt part recited and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</head>
                  <p>TO proue the firſt part, <hi>That Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the infuſion of inherent iuſtice,</hi> he bringeth theſe arguments.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                     </note>The firſt argument (ſaith he) is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3055:29"/>from theſe words of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2</hi> Booke of iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chapt. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>As by the diſobedience of one man, many were made ſinners: ſo by the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of</hi>
                     <hi>one, many ſhall be made iuſt.</hi> 
                     <q>Hence <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> inferreth, that we are made iuſt by obteining inherent iuſtice, both for that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>ſhall be made iuſt:</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, for that he ſaith, <hi>we are ſo made iuſt by Chriſtes obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as we were made vniuſt by</hi> Adams <hi>diſobedience.</hi> But by <hi>Adams</hi> diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience we are made vniuſt, by iniuſtice cleauing within vs indeede.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. It foloweth not: we are made iuſt; therefore by obteining inherent iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: becauſe we may be made iuſt by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of iuſtice. And indeede the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle teacheth that we are made iuſt ſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6. where he ſaith, that <hi>Dauid</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed <hi>the bleſſedneſſe of the man to whome God imputeth iustice.</hi> But that compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Apoſtle, is wreſted to a wrong ſenſe: for the Apoſtle would ſay; As vnto all naturally borne of <hi>Adam</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice is imputed for his diſobedience: ſo to all that beleeue in Chriſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto Chriſt, iuſtice is imputed for his obedience, to wit, wherewith hee obeyed his father, in ſuffering the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them. And although it is true,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3055:30"/>that Chriſt by that his obedience, hath obteined alſo that iuſtice is infuſed into the elect by the regeneration of the holy Ghoſt; as <hi>Adam</hi> by his diſobedience cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that iniuſtice is infuſed into his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie by carnal generation: neuertheleſſe the Apoſtle ſpeaketh not heere of that thing, becauſe heere he handleth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation (which he handleth in the 6.7. and 8. chapters) but iuſtification.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond argument for inherent iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Bellarmine</hi> taketh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied freely by his grace.</hi> That is (ſaith <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi>) by iuſtice giuen &amp; infuſed of him.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere with them of ſound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: that by the name <hi>grace,</hi> here is not meant any infuſed or inherent gift, but Gods fauour and good wil which he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth towards vs. As in many other places in this diſputation: as is to be ſeene in the ſayings recited before, for to confirme the ſixt part of the ſentence of the profeſſon of the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>Againſt this anſwere <hi>Bellarmine</hi> excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: that gods fauour is explained inough <q>by that word, <hi>freely;</hi> in that addition ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>by grace,</hi> is ſignified the effect of his fauour. Then (ſaith he) the prepoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>per, by,</hi> is not rightly applied to fauour, that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3055:30"/>it be ſaid, God by his fauour iuſtifieth vs. Moreouer, the good will of God effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that good which it willeth to any; and Gods will is, that we be truly iuſt and holy before him.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Although Gods fauour he ſignified ynough by the word <hi>[dorean, a. freely]</hi> yet becauſe by that aduerb there is not expreſſed the author of this gift whereof we ſpeake; it pleaſed the Apoſtle for more full declaration ſake to adde, <hi>té autoú chariti,</hi> by, (or <hi>through</hi>) <hi>his,</hi> (that is, Gods) <hi>grace;</hi> by a certaine appoſition. Then, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> aſſumeth falſly, that the Apoſtle heere vſeth the prepoſition <hi>per, .i. by.</hi> Moreouer he frameth a falſe poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when he ſaith the prepoſition <hi>per .i. by,</hi> is not rightly applied to fauour. For the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary is gathered by th'Apoſtles words <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.6. where he ſaith, <hi>to the praiſe of the glory of his grace, in which (en hé) he hath made vs accepted, &amp;c.</hi> Heere it is certaine, by the name <hi>grace,</hi> is vnderſtood the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or good will of God: for this is the ſubiect of the praiſe whereof the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle treateth. Then, this alſo is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that <hi>[en hé] in which,</hi> is put by an hebrue proprietie, for <hi>[di hes] by which.</hi> Laſtly, the good will of God effecteth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3055:31"/>in deed, that we be truly holy: but it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth not that we be perfectly holy in this life, ſo as that we can ſtand in the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God by the holineſſe inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in vs: but effecteth that we are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for perfectly holy, for the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made by Chriſt: of which benefit the Apoſtle here properly ſpeaketh, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by his words.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The third argument he taketh from 1. <hi>Cor. 6.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>3.</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> And ſuch were ye; but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are iustified. Hence <hi>Bellarmine</hi> inferreth, that iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation conteineth theſe two: purgation or waſhing, and ſanctification.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. This conſequence cannot be firmely drawen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtles words. Then this is not the Apoſties mind, that ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is part of iuſtification: which may be gathered by this, that in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> hauing ended the diſputation about Iuſtification, he trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of Sanctification apart by it ſelfe, to wit, in the 6.7. and 8. chapters. And thoſe three things by the ſentence of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, are thus compared among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Firſt by the word <hi>waſhing,</hi> he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth in generall, metaphorically hoth the benefits of Chriſt, to wit, ſanctification &amp;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3055:31"/>iuſtification: which afterwards he addeth for ſpeciall explication ſake. Moreouer, the things that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in this place doth further inferre from thoſe words, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of iuſtice, ſhall more fitly be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered otherwhere.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The 4. argument he taketh from <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. <hi>When the bounty &amp; humanity of God our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour appeared: not by works which we did, but according to his mercy he ſaued vs, by the lauer of regeneration and renouation of the holy Ghoſt, which he hath ſhed into vs abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly through Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour: that being iustified by his grace, we may be heires according to the hope of eternal life.</hi> From thoſe laſt words, <hi>that being iuſtified by his grace,</hi> we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) that iuſtification of deſcribed in the former words: ſo that, after the Apoſtles mind, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is regeneration and renouation through the goodneſſe of God wrought in vs by the lauer of Baptiſme, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out of the holy Ghoſt. Alſo, in thoſe words, <hi>that being iuſtified by his grace, &amp;c.</hi> he ſheweth the cauſe (ſaith he) why God hath regenerate &amp; renued vs by the lauer and holy Ghoſt: and ſaith, the cauſe was, <hi>that being iuſtified,</hi> that is, being iuſtified
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3055:32"/>by that regeneration and renouation, <hi>we may deſerue to be made heyres of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame and life euerlasting.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> as his manner is, confoundeth and taketh for one and the ſame, the things which in the Apoſtle are manifeſtly diuerſe: to wit, regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and iuſtification; and to obteine this, he giueth a gloſſe vpon thoſe words, <hi>that being iuſtified:</hi> ſaying, <hi>that is to ſay, that being iuſtified by that regeneration:</hi> which gloſſe notwithſtanding might be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if it were rightly vnderſtood, namely of the procreant cauſe of faith, and not of the formall cauſe of iuſtification. For by regeneration, the holy Ghoſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth faith in the elect, whereby they apprehend the grace of Chriſt, that is, Chriſts ſatisfaction through Gods grace performed for them. And this is it which the Apoſtle ſaith in this place, <hi>that being iuſtified by his grace, &amp;c.</hi> That is to ſay, hauing by regeneration the gift of faith, we apprehend the grace of Chriſt, and ſo are iuſtified, and obteine the inheritance of eternall life.</p>
                  <p>The 5. argument he taketh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> II. where the Apoſtle teſtifieth (ſaith he) that ſome men were truly and abſolutely iuſt:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>5.</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:3055:32"/>for of <hi>Abel</hi> he writeth, <hi>He obteyned te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie that he was iuſt.</hi> Of <hi>Noah, Hee was made heyre of the iuſtice which is by faith.</hi>
                     <q> And this their iuſtice (ſaith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> further) was not the iuſtice of Chriſe imputed: but iuſtice inherent and proper to them. For the Apoſtle wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſhew, from whence <hi>Abel</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined teſtimonie of iuſtice, ſaith, <hi>God giuing testimonie to his gifis.</hi> Where we ſee, that <hi>Abels</hi> iuſtice is proued by the effect of his iuſtice; to wit, becauſe hee did good works, when he ſacrificed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God aright. Now the cauſe of a good worke is inherent iuſtice, not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of iuſtice: which ſeeing it is outward, cannot be the beginning of the worke. So alſo that <hi>Noe</hi> was iuſt, the Apoſtle prooueth in the ſame place: <hi>Becauſe hee beleeued God, feared Gods iudgement, obeyed Gods commaundement.</hi> And in <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 6. he is ſayd to be iuſt, becauſe <hi>he walked with God.</hi> Euen as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Saint <hi>Luke</hi> prooueth (Chapter. 1.) that <hi>Zacharie</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> were <hi>iuſt before God,</hi> becauſe <hi>they walked in all the commaundements and iuſtifications of the Lord.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:3055:33"/>
I anſwere. The fraud of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is to be marked, who that he might wreſt that place of <hi>Abel</hi> to his purpoſe, reciteth it vnperfitly: leauing out theſe two words <hi>By which,</hi> which do agree in the ſame ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence with thoſe words which he citeth, and pertaine greatly vnto the queſtion in hand. For ſo ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>Abel by faith offered a more pretious ſacrifice then Cain;</hi> By which, <hi>he obteined teſtimonie that he was iuſt, God bearing witneſſe of his gifts.</hi> Where it is manifeſt, that faith is made the procreant cauſe both of the pretiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of <hi>Abels</hi> ſacrifice, and alſo of <hi>Abels</hi> iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and laſtly alſo of the teſtimonie, whereby God bare witneſſe that <hi>Abel</hi> was iuſt by faith, and therefore that his ſacrifice was pretious and pleaſed him. Wherefore it is plaine, that here he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the iuſtice of faith. Which thing appeareth yet more manifeſtly by the other teſtimonie; namely, that <hi>Noe was made heyre of the iustice which is by faith.</hi> Which teſtimonie it is ſtrange that <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> would cite heere, ſeeing it plainly repugneth his purpoſe. For <hi>the iuſtice of faith,</hi> is the iuſtice which God imputeth to man, as is euident by the words of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3055:33"/>the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord imputeth iustice.</hi> Moreouer, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> feigneth a falſe drift of the Apoſtles words; as though he would proue, that <hi>Abel</hi> was iuſt: and as though he proued it by this, that he did a good worke, by ſacrificing a right. But the Apoſtle hath another purpoſe, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by <hi>Abels'</hi> example to proue, that both man himſelfe and his workes pleaſe God by faith. Beſides he falſly denieth, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted iuſtice is the cauſe of a iuſt worke. For except iuſtice be imputed to a man by ſaith, no worke of his can pleaſe God and be approued as <hi>Iust.</hi> For <hi>without faith</hi> (as the Apoſtle there ſaith) <hi>it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi> Neither doth it hinder, that imputation of iuſtice (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) is outward. For faith, by which iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is imputed to man, is (that I may ſo ſay) inward, that is, ſeated within: and this is it which worketh by loue. But as concerning thoſe places, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. of <hi>Noe,</hi> and <hi>Luke.</hi> 1. of <hi>Zacharie</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> their begun inherent iuſtice, is there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, by the adioyned ſinceritie: to wit, for that they minded, that God was the beholder of all their actions: and thereupon ſtudied to approue them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3055:34"/>him: and it is not meant, that they tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted vpon that iuſtice of their life before God, as being perfect, and in all things an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his law, for which eternall life ought to be adiudged them of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The 6. Argument hee taketh from <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49. where the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">6. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>that the iust are confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the Image of Chriſt, &amp; beare Chriſts Image, Thoſe whom he fore-knew</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>them he praedeſtinated to be made conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Image of his ſonne.</hi> And <hi>as we haue borne the Image of the earthy, we ſhall beare alſo the Image of the heauenly. Bellarmine</hi> aſſumeth: now Chriſt is not iuſt by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, but by iuſtice inherent to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. He concludeth: therefore it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that wee alſo haue inherent iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here firſt <hi>Bellarmine</hi> vſeth a fallacie from that which is ſpoken in reſpect, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which is ſpoken ſimplie: whiles he taketh thoſe ſpeeches of the Apoſtle which are ſpoken properly of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of the beleeuers with Chriſt in glorie, as if they were ſpoken of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in all things. For otherwiſe he could not thence inferre, that wee ought to be conformed vnto Chriſt euen in this alſo,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3055:34"/>that we be not iuſt by imputation. Then he deceitfully leaueth out in the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the one part of the aſſumption: when as the whole concluſion is this: therefore we alſo are not iuſt by imputation, but by inherent iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>The firſt part of which concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on manifeſtly contradicteth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, who ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>The man is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to whom God imputeth iustice.</hi> Finally that concluſion of <hi>Bellarmines,</hi> maketh nothing for the queſtion in hand. For the queſtion is not, whither it be neceſſarie that we haue inherent iuſtice: but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by inherent iuſtice wee can ſtand in Gods iudgement and be iuſtified of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> proceedeth to reaſon from that place to the Corinthes thus. Wee haue borne the true Image of the earthly man, that is, of the ſinner <hi>Adam:</hi> becauſe ſinne cleaued in vs not puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, but in truth and in deed: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we beare alſo Chriſts true Image, if iuſtice cleaue in vs, not putatiuely, but in truth and in deed.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here <hi>Bellarmine</hi> deceitfully in ſtead of the word <hi>Imputation,</hi> putteth as equall thereto, the word <hi>Putation:</hi> ſaying
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3055:35"/>
                     <hi>putatiuely,</hi> for <hi>imputatiuely:</hi> that he might note a certaine vaine opinion, whereunto no matter ſubſiſteth. Yet in the meane while <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is not ignorant, that not onely the ſinne which dwelleth in man ſince the fall, is deriued from <hi>Adam</hi> vnto his poſteritie by generation: but alſo that firſt ſinne committed properly by <hi>Adam,</hi> is imputed to his poſteritie. And by like reaſon, not onely inherent iuſtice, that is, ſtudy of godlineſſe in thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto Chriſt, is wrought by Chriſt through regeneration of the holy Ghoſt: but alſo that obedience of Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſatisfied for the ſinnes of the elect, is imputed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the iuſtice where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſtand before God. Moreouer, he concludeth not heere the queſtion, which is not, whether wee ſhall beare Chriſtes Image as touching inherent iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: for no profeſſor of the Goſpell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth this: but the queſtion is, whether by this iuſtice we can ſtand in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The 7. argument hee draweth from <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. where the Apoſtle teacheth (ſaith he) that we through Iuſtification,<note place="margin">7. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                        </note> whereby we die to ſinne, and riſe againe to iuſtice, do repreſent Chriſts death and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3055:35"/>reſurrection. And amongſt other things ſaith, <hi>He that is dead, is iustified from ſinne.</hi> Which alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſignified in his firſt Epiſtle, Chap. 4. when he ſaith, <hi>Chriſt therefore hauing ſuffered in the fleſh, be ye alſo armed with the ſame minde. For he that hath ſuffered in the fleſh, hath cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from ſinnes.</hi> But Chriſt was not puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, but truly dead, &amp; truly roſe again: therefore we alſo do not putatiuely but truly die to ſinne, and riſe againe to iuſtice, when wee are iuſtified by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Firſt it is falſe, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. teacheth, that wee by Iuſtification do repreſent Chriſts death and reſurrection. For hee treateth not there of Iuſtification, hauing made an end of that diſpute in in the 5. Chapter: but he treateth of ſanctification or rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. Neither can it bee proued o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, from thoſe words: <hi>He that is dead, is iuſtified from ſinne.</hi> For the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh not there of mans Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before God, but vſeth the word <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified</hi> for <hi>Freed,</hi> by a ſynechdoche of the <hi>ſpecies.</hi> For euery one that is iuſtified, that is to ſay, is quitted by the Iudge, is freed: to wit, from puniſhment: but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3055:36"/>one that is freed, is not iuſtified: for one may be freed from ſome other thing then from puniſhment; as, from ſinne. And of this freeing ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>He that is dead is iuſtified from ſinne:</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee that is dead cannot worke ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or euill. Therefore beleeuen in as much as they are dead to ſinne, (as the Apoſtle there ſaith, verſe, 11.) ſo far forth they are freed from ſinne. Euen as a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by death is freed from his maiſter, that he ſerue him not any more hereafter, as the Apoſtle ſaith in the words imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately going before, <hi>That our old man is crucified with Chriſt, that the body of ſinne may be weakened, that hereafter we ſerue ſo no more.</hi> Then it is true, that wee do tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly die to ſinne and riſe againe to iuſtice: but the queſtion is not of this thing: but it is, whether by this ſpirituall death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection (that is to ſay, inherent iuſtice) we be iuſtified before God. Finally <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> comprehendeth more in the concluſion, then followeth of the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes where he ſaith, <hi>When we are iuſtified by faith:</hi> in which very thing hee beggeth the queſtion. For the Apoſtle ſayth not in the place cited: that we are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Baptiſme: ſeeing hee handleth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3055:36"/>nothing there of <hi>Iustification:</hi> but tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that Baptiſme is a teſtimonie of our regeneration, which is wrought by the holy Ghoſt, in as much as it teacheth vs of Chriſts death and reſurrection. For it being taught by the holy Ghoſt, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that Chriſt died for our ſinnes, and roſe againe vnto heauenly life, as our firſt fruites and head: certainly wee will ſtudy to auoyde ſinnes, and will meditate an heauenlie and an holie life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The 8. Argument hee taketh from <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. where the Apoſtle (ſaith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>) writeth,<note place="margin">7. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>That wee now by Chriſt haue receiued the ſpirit of adoption of ſonnes of God, as touching the ſoule, which liueth</hi> (as there is ſaid) <hi>becauſe of Iustification: though the body be dead,</hi> (that is, be yet mortall) <hi>becauſe of ſinne.</hi> But by and by after hee addeth (to wit, the Apoſtle) <hi>that we now hauing the firſt fruites of the ſpirit, doo ſigh in our ſelues, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the adoption of the ſonnes of God, the redemption of our body.</hi> For as the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>Wee expect a Sauiour which will reforme the body of our humilitie, configured to the body of his glory.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:3055:37"/>
But the adoption of ſonnes which we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect in the redemption of our body, ſhall be moſt true and inherent in the body: that is, immortalitie, and impaſſibilitie, not imputatiue, but true. Therefore the adoption which now we haue in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by Iuſtification, ought alſo to be true, not putatiue. Otherwiſe as we expect the redemption of the body, ſo alſo we expect the redemption of the ſoule.</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Firſt <hi>Bellarmine</hi> faulteth in a falſe expoſition: in as much as he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the name <hi>body</hi> ſimplie for the body of man: and contrariwiſe, the name <hi>ſpirit</hi> for the ſoule. For the Apoſtle there by the name <hi>body,</hi> vnderſtandeth that which in that and other places hee calleth <hi>fleſh:</hi> that is, the body together with the ſoule, but ſuch as it is by carnall generation: and likewiſe by the name <hi>ſpirit,</hi> he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth the ſoule with the body; but ſo far forth as the ſoule is regenerate by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>Next, he faulteth in falſe citation: for the Apoſtle writeth not, <hi>The ſoule liueth becauſe of Iuſtification;</hi> but <hi>The ſpirit is life, becauſe of Iuſtice.</hi> Then againe he faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in falſe expoſition; in as much as he expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth thoſe words, <hi>The body is dead,</hi>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:3055:37"/>to meane, <hi>Is yet mortall:</hi> when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles meaning is, that by the holy Ghoſt dwelling in the beleeuers, it commeth to paſſe that their fleſh is mortified as touching ſinne; to wit ſo, as that it ſinne not: and the ſpirite is quickned as concerning iuſtice, to wit ſo, as that it endeuoureth for iuſtice and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it. That this is the meaning of thoſe words, may plainly appeare to any that marketh, by the words there next enſuing. Moreouer <hi>Bellarmines</hi> ſophiſme, from a like reaſon of the adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body, and the adoption of the ſoule, is vtterly darke, and farre from the Apoſtles words and meaning. For neither doth the Apoſtle ſay, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption to come in the body; nor yet, that wee now haue adoption in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; that is, in the ſoule: neither doth hee compare theſe two adoptions as like one to an other. But hee ſayth, <hi>Wee expect the adoption of the ſonnes of God:</hi> that is to ſay, that heauenly inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, which wee are adopted to poſſeſſe and enioy in due time. And this very thing hee calleth <hi>redemption of the body:</hi> that is to ſay redemption, whereby both the body ſhall be deliuered from
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3055:38"/>the croſſe whereto it is ſubiect in this life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the ſoule, from inhabiting ſinne, wherein it is holden, ſo long as it liueth in this mortall body. Wherefore it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt, and not beſeeming a Diuine, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> counteth this an abſurd thing, that we ſhould looke for redemption of the ſoule. For that lamentation of <hi>Paule, Rom.</hi> 7.24. <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of death?</hi> doth it not pertaine to the ful deliuerance of the ſoule from inhabiting ſinne. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is a true, and not a putatiue adoption (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> cauelling ſpeaketh) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God hath adopted vs: and yet the adoption, is the imputation of ſonne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, whereby wee are counted for the ſonnes of God through grace: when by nature wee were the children of wrath. But in the meane time, <hi>adoption</hi> is one thing, <hi>the ſpirit of adoption</hi> an other thing. By adoption we are receiued into grace, and iuſtified: by the ſpirit of adoption, we are regenerate, beeing already adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:3055:38"/>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The proofe of the ſecond part recited and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</head>
                  <p>HItherto we haue diſputed of the firſt part of the Papiſts opinion, wherin they determine, that Iuſtification is infuſion of iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>It followeth that now wee treate of the ſecond parte, wherein they ſay, <hi>That faith alone iustifieth not, but</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>I.</hi> principall Argument the proofes wherof do follow. <hi>I.</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>I</hi> Booke of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chap. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>as the beginning and roote of Iustification.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To proue this, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> firſt brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>Hee that commeth vnto God, muſt beleeue that God is.</hi> Where the firſt motion vnto God, is giuen to faith; by which he that was far off, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth now to draw nigh.</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. The Apoſtle here ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no compariſon betweene faith and other ſpirituall vertues: but ſpeaking ſimplie of faith alone, affirmeth it to bee neceſſarie for him that commeth vnto God, to wit, to craue his helpe, and aske any thing of him. Wherfore it is a ſtrange gloſſe, that the firſt motion vnto God is here giuen to faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:3055:39"/>
As though the motions that follow, were not of faith, but of other ſpiritual vertues: And as though Iuſtification were done by I know not how many motions vnto God. Nay, Iuſtification is made by this onely motion, wherby the mind through faith is ſo moued vnto God, that it taketh hold of his good will, reconciled by Chriſts ſatisfaction to all that beleeue in him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Then hee bringeth the ſaying <hi>Rom.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                        </note> 10. <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall call vpon the name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaued. But how ſhall they call vpon him, in whom they haue not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? how ſhall they beleeue without a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher? how ſhall they preach except they bee ſent?</hi> Where the Apoſtle deſeribeth this order of luſtification, that firſt there be a ſending of Preachers: ſecondly, the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell: thirdly, faith: fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, inuocation: fiftly, ſaluation: that is, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifications,</hi> which is health of ſoule, from the diſeaſe of ſinne. Of which ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and preaching, are without vs: and and to the firſt beginning of <hi>Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in vs, is faith: after which followeth inuocation and the reſt in their order.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>I anſwere. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> faulteth faſt in confuſion of things diuerſe, in that be
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3055:39"/>expoundeth the word <hi>Saluation,</hi> by the word <hi>Iustification<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> when as Saluation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſpoken, is more large, to wit, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending iuſtification, regeneration, and glorification.</q> Then hee faulteth in a falſe definition: when as hee defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Iuſtification to bee health of ſoule from the diſeaſe of ſinne: that is to ſay, regeneration. Finally, he goeth from the queſtion, in that hee numbreth certaine things which be needfull vnto ſaluation beſides faith. For when the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Goſpell teach, that man is iuſtified by faith onely: they exclude not thoſe things that are here reckoned, from the obtaining of ſaluation: but only they exclude mans workes from obtaining that ruſtice which God may approoue as perfect.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, he bringeth the place <hi>Iohn.</hi> I. <hi>So many as receiued him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>he gaue them power to be made the ſons of God, to thoſe that beleeue</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>in his name.</hi> Here <hi>Iohn</hi> ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly teacheth (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) that they which receiue Chriſt by faith, are not yet the ſons of God, but may ſo be made, if they go on further, that they alſo begin to hope and loue. For loue properly maketh the ſonnes of God, as as appeareth, I. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:3055:40"/>
I anſwere. The meaning of <hi>Iohn</hi> words, is not that which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth: but he meaneth, that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the beleeuers power or right <hi>[ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſian] for to be made the ſonnes of God, that is, to be the ſonnes of God,</hi> in this very reſpect, that they are borne of God (as be declareth in the verſe following) that is, that they are regenerate, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence endued with faith. Whence I draw this Argument:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As farre forth as the beleeuers are borne of God, ſo farre forth is giuen vnto them the right of the children of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the beleeuers as far foorth as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, are borne of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore to the beleeuers as far forth a they beleeue, is giuen the right of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God: and by conſequence, they are iuſtified as far foxth as they beleeue, or, by faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And whereas <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, it is plaine by 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. that loue properly maketh the ſonnes of God: verily I find not this ſentence in that Chapter, neither expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor yet by collection: But if perhaps through the Printers fault, the number ſecond crept in for the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber third, there is indeed in the third Chapter a certaine
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3055:40"/>ſentence of loue, but not this. <hi>That loue maketh the ſonnes of God; but, that by loue the ſonnes of God are knowne: namely in the</hi> 10. verſe. <hi>By this are manifeſted the ſonnes of God, and the ſonnes of the diuell: Who ſo doth not iuſtice, is not of God, and he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not his brother.</hi> Neither can <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> ſentence be concluded (as hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture thinketh) from the 1. <hi>verſe,</hi> where it is ſaid thus, <hi>Behold what loue the father hath giuen to vs, that we ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſonnes of God.</hi> For by the name <hi>Loue</hi> there, by a <hi>metonymie</hi> of the efficient cauſe, he vnderſtandeth a benefit procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the loue wherewith God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs: and what that benefit is, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth by oppoſition in thoſe words, <hi>that we ſhould be called the ſonnes of God:</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the benefit of adoption. Wherefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath not yet ſhewed, that we are adopted and iuſtified of GOD by loue, and therefore not by faith onely.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>To theſe Arguments <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a naturall reaſon,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                        </note> as hee calleth it in theſe words. Some man may beleeue that which he hopeth not for, neither loueth: be cannot hope for, or loue that which he beleeueth not. Therefore faith is the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3055:41"/>foundation of hope and loue: and not contrariwiſe, hope or loue, the foundation of faith.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. In this reaſon, the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not concluded. Which is not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faith be the foundation or originall of hope and loue: but whether we be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith only, or by faith hope and loue together.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Vnto this reaſon he ioyneth an other: in bodily diſeaſes the beginning of health is,<note place="margin">5. Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> to beleeue that he is ſicke, and to haue faith in the Phiſitian that is willing to cure: yet is not that onely faith, perfect health.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Firſt <hi>Bellarmine</hi> vnaptly maketh the ſick ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s faith a part of health whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it is the procreant cauſe of health: in as much as the ſick man ſhould not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine health, except he had that faith. In like manner faith whereby we are iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is not a part of Iuſtification: but the procreant inſtrumental cauſe, becauſe by faith we apprehend Chriſts ſatisfaction, for which we are iuſtified. Next as his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is, he confoundeth iuſtification with regeneration: in as much as hee calleth faith <hi>health,</hi> towit, of ſoule, vnderſtanding newneſſe of nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:3055:41"/>
Moreouer, he falſly defineth faith where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are iuſtified: to wit, as though by it we beleeued only, that we are ſpiritually ſick, that is to ſay, ſinners: and that the ſpirituall phiſitian Chriſt, is willing to cure vs. But theſe ſuffice not vnto iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith: but it is required further, that we beleeue that Chriſt hath already per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured vs by his ſatisfaction, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: and hath begun to cure vs, as touching renuing of nature: and finally, as touching the ſame, is willing perfectly to cure vs, and alſo will cure vs after this life. Wherefore there is not the like reaſon of the faith which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in this place attributeth to a ſick man, and of iuſtifying faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that feare concurreth vnto iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> proceedeth vnto the ſecond diſpoſition (as he after the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> nameth it) whereby they feigne a man is diſpoſed vnto iuſtification, that is to ſay, <hi>Feare.</hi> And indeuoureth to proue by the places of ſcripture folowing, that this concurreth vnto iuſtification, almoſt after the ſame manner that faith it ſelfe concurreth.</p>
                  <p>Firſt (ſaith he) we haue learned by the Apoſtle, that faith iuſtifieth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>I.</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> when hee ſaith, <hi>Without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe"
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3055:42"/>God,</hi> Hebr. 11. But the ſame is alſo ſaid of Feare; <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> 1. <hi>He that is without feare, cannot be iustified.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere, Firſt, the teſtimonie of <hi>Eccleſiasticus</hi> is not of force to proue any poynt of faith: becauſe that booke is not Canonicall, but Apocryphall. Then, though that booke were of authoritie; yet the ſaying alleadged would proue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: becauſe here is brought a falſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, which containeth a plain di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe ſentence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in the Greek words of Ieſus the ſon of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach;</hi> which are to be interpreted, <hi>an angry man cannot be iuſtified: for the moment of his anger is ruine vnto him.</hi> Thirdly, althogh it were ſo in the Greek as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> citeth out of the common tranſlation; yet this ſpeech would make nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore for the ſon of <hi>Sirach</hi> ſpeaketh not of mans iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before God; but before the ciuill Iudge: warning, that they which are giuen to anger, or that without the feare of God follow their owne luſts, will at length commit thoſe haynous ſinnes and wickedneſſes, for which beeing brought vnto iudgement, they cannot be iuſtified, that is quitted: but are by the Iudge condemned vnto deſerued
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3055:42"/>puniſhment. Fourthly, although this ſaying of <hi>Syrach</hi> were to be vnderſtood of Iuſtification before God: yet could not the queſtion bee concluded from it.</p>
                  <p>For it is brought as beeing like to that ſaying of the Apoſtle: and from that likeneſſe, is the Argument drawne: when as notwithſtanding it is not like. For it is not ſaid, <hi>Without feare</hi> it is <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be iustified;</hi> as it is ſaid, <hi>Without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God:</hi> but it is ſaid, <hi>Hee that is without feare, cannot bee iustified.</hi> Beſides, though it were ſaid, <hi>Without feare it is impoſſible to be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> as it is ſaid, <hi>without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God:</hi> yet would it not follow from hence, that feare would pertaine vnto Iuſtification, after one and the ſame manner that faith dooth: for faith pertaineth to Iuſtification, as the inſtrumentall cauſe whereby wee take holde on Chriſtes ſatisfaction, for which wee are iuſtified: but the feare of GOD pertaineth as an effect of faith, neceſſarily agreeing therewith. For where the feare of GOD is not, neither is there iuſtyfying faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:3055:43"/>
                     <q>Then,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                        </note> faith iuſtifieth (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) becauſe it is the beginning of iuſtice and ſaluation: But the feare of the Lord is the beginning of wiſedome, <hi>Prou.</hi> I. and by wiſdome is vnderſtood perfect iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Firſt it is falſe, that by wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is vnderſtood iuſtification, for iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is Gods action, whereby he counteth and pronounceth man iuſt: but wiſedome is a qualitie in mans minde, wrought of God. Wherefore that ſaying maketh nothing to the matter. Next, if by the name of wiſedome in <hi>Salomons</hi> ſpeech, were vnderſtoode iuſtification, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> aſſumeth things that mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly cannot ſtand together, and feigneth them vnto the holy Ghoſt that ſpeaketh in the ſcripture: in as much as he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth both faith and feare to be the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of iuſtification. For if faith be the beginning of iuſtification, feare can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be: and ſo contrariwiſe, ſeeing of one thing, there is but one beginning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Moreouer,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                        </note> faith iuſtifieth (ſaith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>) becauſe by it we ſeeke God, and come vnto him. But the ſame thing doth feare. For it is written in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. <hi>When he ſlew them, they ſought him and returned, &amp;c</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:3055:43"/>
I anſwere. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> aſſumeth a falſe thing: for faith iuſtifieth not, becauſe by it we ſeeke God: but becauſe by it we take hold on Chriſtes ſatisfaction, for which God iuſtifieth vs. Which thing cannot be attributed vnto feare.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                     </note> faith iuſtifieth (ſaith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>) becauſe by it Chriſt is formed in vs, as he ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. <q>But of feare, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> writeth, chapt. 26. according to the 70. Greeke interpreters, <hi>By the feare we haue conceiued, and brought forth the ſpirit of ſaluation.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Firſt it is falſe, that it is ſaid in <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. Faith iuſtifieth becauſe by it Chriſt is formed in vs. Yet it is true, that this ſentence may be concluded from the Apoſtles words, which are: <hi>My little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, of whom I trauel in birth againe, vntill Chriſt be formed in you.</hi> By which words the Apoſtle ſignifieth, that he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout by the doctrine of the Goſpell to reduce the <hi>Galathians</hi> to the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and faith of Chriſt. And the ſcope was, that by that faith they might be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified; in as much as by it they ſhould take hold on Chriſtes ſatisfaction. Which taking hold, the Apoſtle metaphorically calleth a forming of Chriſt in the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians:</hi>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:3055:44"/>becauſe he had ſaid, that hee tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled in birth againe of them: that ſo he might continue the metaphor hee had begun. But ſuch forming of Chriſt in man, cannot be aſcribed vnto feare. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can that any way be prooued from that ſaying of <hi>Iſaiah:</hi> in the citing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hitherto, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> bewrayeth his maruellous impudencie: ſeeing that place containeth nothing at all of Chriſt or iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification: no not though the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the 70. be admitted. But why doth not <hi>Bellarmine</hi> cite the common Latin tranſlation; when as notwithſtanding hee approoueth and defendeth the decree of the Councell of <hi>Trent;</hi> wherin is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that the common Latin edition is to be held for authenticall? 2. Booke <hi>De Verbo Des,</hi> Chap. 10. For if that be authe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, that which differeth from it cannot be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for authenticall. And the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the 70. differeth in this place.</p>
                  <p>But if one looke into that place, and conſider the whole context, hee ſhall ſee, that there is nothing at all of Chriſtes or mans iuſtification before God, contained in thoſe words: but a narration of the Iewes, wherein they tell theyr owne weakneſſe in deliuering themſelues from
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3055:44"/>calamities, and purchaſing themſelues ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
                  <p>Their calamities they compare to a woman in trauell, ſaying: <hi>As a woman with child, that draweth neare to the trauell, is in ſorrow, and crieth in her paines, ſo haue we bene in thy ſight ô Lord: We haue concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, we haue borne in paine, as though wee ſhould haue brought forth wind; We could not giue any helpe to the Land.</hi> It is therfore an impudent ſophiſme of <hi>Bellarmine:</hi> who ſhameth not to alleadge theſe things here, as being ſpoken of mans Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>Againe, faith Iuſtifieth (ſaith <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi>) becauſe <hi>the iuſt liueth by faith.</hi> Hab. 2. And of feare it is written, <hi>The feare of the Lord is the fountaine of life.</hi> Prou. 14.</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. It is falſe, that faith iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, becauſe, or in as much as the Iuſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by faith. Neither doth <hi>Habacuck</hi> ſay this, but onely ſaith, <hi>The iuſt ſhall liue by faith.</hi> You contrariwiſe, the iuſt ſhall liue by faith, becauſe hee is iuſtified by faith. For iuſtice goeth before life, as the cauſe before the effect. And faith Iuſtifieth, becauſe, or in as much as it appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth Chriſts ſatisfaction, for which God iuſtifieth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:3055:45"/>
                     <q>To conclude,<note place="margin">6. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                        </note> faith iuſtifieth (ſaith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>) becauſe it purgeth ſinnes, as the Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. and in other places: But of feare alſo we reade, <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 1. <hi>The feare of the Lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth ſinne.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Faith, to ſpeake properly, purgeth not ſinnes, but Chriſtes bloud, 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1. And if faith be ſaid to purge ſinnes, it is to be vnderſtood thus, that it apprehendeth Chriſtes ſatisfaction vnto forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. But after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the feare of the Lord doth not expell ſinne: but ſo farre as it holdeth a man like a bridle, from giuing himſelfe vp to ſinne, and ſinning ſecurely. Neither is it ſaid in any of the places alleaged, that faith purgeth ſinnes. But <hi>Act.</hi> 15.9. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>that God had purged the harts of the beleeuing Gentiles by faith:</hi> that is, had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen them their ſinnes by faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they apprehended Chriſts ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. it is ſaid, <hi>That God hath ſet forth Chriſt to be a propitiation by faith in his bloud, to declare his iustice by forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of foredone ſins.</hi> In <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. there is no ſuch thing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Laſt of all he addeth this reaſon:<note place="margin">7. <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                        </note> The nature of feare is (ſaith he) to flee euils,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3055:45"/>and ſeeke remedies how it may eſcape them.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. But hence it foloweth not that feare iuſtifieth; and that after the ſame manner that faith doth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that hope of pardon is a dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition vnto iustice and remiſſion of ſinnes.</note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> proceedeth to the third diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as he calleth it, to wit, <hi>Hope:</hi> namely, hope to obtaine pardon. That this is a diſpoſition vnto iuſtice and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, he proueth by theſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. <hi>Prou.</hi> 28. <hi>He that hopeth in the Lord, ſhalbe healed, Pſal.</hi> 36. <hi>He wil ſaue them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they hoped in him. Pſal.</hi> 90. <hi>Becauſe he hoped in me, I will deliuer him. Mat.</hi> 9. <hi>Haue confidence ſome, thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee:</hi> where he noteth, <q>that the Lord firſt ſaid, <hi>Haue confidence ſonne:</hi> and when he ſawe him lifted vp vnto the hope of ſaluation, he added, <hi>Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Firſt, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſtrayeth from the queſtion. For the queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed is, whether onely faith iuſtifieth; and not, whether it onely diſpoſe vnto iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification: wherefore he ſhould proue, that hope alſo iuſtifieth, and not, that hope diſpoſeth vnto iuſtification. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, the ſayings all eaged out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs and Pſalmes, make nothing to the matter: for none of them ſpeake of the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3055:46"/>obtaining of the forgiuenes of ſinnes, but they ſpeake of outward felicitie, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance from outward dangers. Neither is there in that place of the Prouerbs, in the Hebrue, the word <hi>bealed:</hi> but <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſhalbe made fat.</hi> Neither in the ſaid 90. Pſalme, or after the Hebrues di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ction, the 91. Pſalme, is the Hebrue; <hi>becauſe he hoped in me:</hi> but <hi>becauſe he hath loued me,</hi> or, <hi>bene louingly affected vnto me.</hi> Finally, in none of theſe places is there ſpeech of hope of obtaining pardon, of which the queſtion was propounded: but there is ſpeech of hope of the fatherly prouidence and care of God towards his children. Now as touching that ſaying, <hi>Math.</hi> 9. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> wreſteth it vnto his purpoſe, by a falſe interpretation of the word, <hi>Haue confidence:</hi> as if it were the ſame that <hi>Conceiue hope of pardon</hi> is. Then he maket'd a weake conſequence. If the Lord ſaid firſt, <hi>Haue confidence:</hi> and after, <hi>Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee.</hi> Therfore that confidence of which he ſpake, went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forgiuenes of ſinnes. Laſtly he folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the falſe interpretation of the word <hi>[aphéontas] forgiuen,</hi> which ſignifieth not <hi>are forgiuen,</hi> but, <hi>haue bene forgiuen,</hi> for it is not of the time preſent, but paſt. And
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3055:46"/>the naturall ſenſe of the words is this: Haue confidence ſonne, that thou ſhalt obtaine of me healing of thy palſie: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt already obtained a farre greater benefit, to wit, forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. But if that were the ſenſe which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> giueth the word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould ſound thus, <hi>Haue confidence ſonne, and thy ſinnes ſhalbe forgiuen thee:</hi> that is (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would haue it) Conceiue hope of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, or forgiueneſſe of ſinnes; for if thou ſo do, it ſhall be done vnto thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that loue diſpoſeth vnto for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes.</note>The fourth diſpoſition (ſaith <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> further) is loue. Now that ſome loue is before forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, either in time, if it be imperfect loue, or in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if it be perfect and from the whole heart, <hi>Eccleſiasticus</hi> teacheth firſt (ſaith he) chapt. 2. For after that he had ſayd, <hi>Yee that feare the Lord, truſt in him,</hi> hee addeth, <q>
                        <hi>Yee that feare the Lord, loue him, and your harts ſhall be inlightned.</hi> Then alſo our Sauiour himſelfe teacheth it, when hee ſaith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7. <hi>Many ſinnes are forgiuen her, becauſe ſhee loued much.</hi> Alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> teacheth it, when he writeth, <hi>Galath.</hi> 5. <hi>Neither Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion auaileth any thing, nor Vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion: but faith which worketh by loue.</hi>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:3055:47"/>The Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> teacheth the ſame, 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. ſaying, <hi>We are tranſlated from death to life, becauſe we loue the brethren.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. As touching that place in <hi>Eccleſiasticus:</hi> it is not of force to proue any point of faith, becauſe the booke is Apocryphal. Then, that ſentence is not found in the Greeke copie. Thirdly, he treateth not there of remiſſion of ſinnes, wherefore this ſentence is nothing to the purpoſe. As concerning the other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Luc.</hi> 7. the coniunction <hi>becauſe,</hi> in Greeke <hi>[hóti,]</hi> noteth not the cauſe of the <hi>thing,</hi> but the cauſe of the <hi>concluſion:</hi> that is the argument, whereby the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence propoſed is proued. And that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was drawen not from the cauſe, but from the effect. For, that many ſinnes are forgiuen this woman, Chriſt proueth by her deede, as an effect of the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes, which ſhe perceiued ſhe had obteyned by the grace of Chriſt. As is plaine by the Simile, which the Lord addeth to declare that deede, to wit, the creditor, which forgaue two debtors, to the one, more; to the other, leſſe: whereupon it came, that the one loued him more, the other leſſe. As therefore that loue of the debtors, was not the cauſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3055:47"/>of forgiuing the det: but contrarywiſe, the forgiuing of the det, was cauſe of their loue: ſo alſo the loue of that woman, was not the cauſe why Chriſt forgaue her her ſinnes: but contrariwiſe, the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes, was cauſe why the woman loued him. Neither is this declaration anſwered, by the expoſition which <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> bringeth in an other place, that the coniunction <hi>[hóti] becauſe,</hi> is a cauſal. For it is not named a cauſal, for that it ſignifieth the cauſe of the thing, but for that it ſignifieth the cauſe of the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: that is, the argument or <hi>medium</hi> of the proofe.</p>
                  <p>From the words <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. it cannot be gathered, that loue diſpoſeth vnto iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: but onely we are taught, what maner of faith that is whereby we are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, namely faith working by loue.</p>
                  <p>In the place out of the Epiſtle of <hi>Iohn, Bellarmine</hi> hath committed the crime of falſhood, for that he hath cited the text vnperfectly, that he might wreſt it vnto his purpoſe. For it is not there, <hi>We are tranſlated, &amp;c.</hi> but, <hi>We know that we are tranſlated.</hi> It is euident therefore, that loue is not there made the cauſe of our tranſlation from death to life: but the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3055:48"/>ſigne and argument, whereby we know that we are tranſlated. And loue is the ſigne of this thing: becauſe it is the effect of true faith, by which that tranſlation is made, as our Lord witneſſeth, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.24. <hi>He that beleeueth, hath paſſed from death into life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The ſecond principall argument.</note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> proceedeth to another prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall argument; which he concludeth in this reaſoning: If faith be ſeparated from <q>hope and loue and other vertues, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt it cannot iuſtifie: Therefore onely faith cannot iuſtifie. The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of this argument is proued ſaith he, thus: If the whole force of iuſtifying were in faith only, ſo that other vertues though they were preſent, conferred no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all vnto iuſtification;</q> ſurely that faith would iuſtifie<note n="*" place="margin">It ſhould be, as well when they are abſent as preſent.</note> as well when they are preſent, as abſent. Therefore, if it cannot iuſtifie when they are abſent, it argueth that the force of iuſtifying is not in it onely, but partly in it, partly in the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Alſo: If it cannot be, that faith ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from loue ſhould iuſtifie; then it alone iuſtifieth not. But the firſt is true: for without loue there can be no iuſtice: becauſe he that loueth not, abideth in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3055:48"/>death, 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2. Therefore the latter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is true. Beſides, if faith ſeparated from vertues can iuſtifie, it can alſo doo the ſame with vices: for as the preſence of other vertues profiteth faith nothing, as concerning the dutie of iuſtifying, becauſe it onely iuſtifieth: ſo the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of vices ſhall nothing hinder it as touching the office of iuſtifying: becauſe by accident, there are ioyned with it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vices or vertues. But the conſequent is abſurd: therefore alſo the antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. All theſe connexe or (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> calleth them) conditionate propoſitions of theſe three reaſons, are falſe. For although faith be not alone, but hath other vertues ioyned with it, and not vices (which is impoſſible:) yet faith onely iuſtifieth. Euen as the hand of a writer, although it be not alone, but ioyned with the other members: yet it onely writeth. And as the foote as not alone, but ioyned to the other members, yet it onely ſtandeth. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as the eye is not alone, and yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſeeth: the eare is not alone, but yet heareth alone. Finally, the members of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3055:49"/>mans body, although they be ioyned one to another, and cannot do their ſeuerall actions, except they be ioyned one to another, yet haue euery one their proper action.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The third principall argument.</note>The third principall argument, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would proue that faith iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth not alone; is taken (ſaith he) from <q>the remouing away of the cauſes which may be giuen why faith onely iuſtifieth. For all ſuch cauſes may be reduced (ſaith he) vnto three heads. And thus he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth.</q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>If faith alone iustifieth: either it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore iustifieth alone becauſe the ſcripture ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely ſaith it; or becauſe it pleaſed God to giue iustification with the onely condition of faith: or becauſe it alone hath the force to apprehend iustification, and apply it vnto vs, and make it ours.</p>
                     <p>But none of theſe cauſes can truly be ſaid of faith.</p>
                     <p>Therefore neither can it be truly ſaid of it, that it onely iuſtifieth.</p>
                     <p>The firſt part of the aſſumption he ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth to proue by this, that in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture there is found an expreſſe denyall of that word (to wit, <hi>Onely</hi>) or a word of the ſame ſignification: namely, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. <hi>Yee ſee
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3055:49"/>that of workes a man is iuſtified, and not of faith onely.</hi> The ſecond part he proueth by this, that ſcriptures doo much more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly require the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of repentance and of the Sacraments vnto Iuſtification, then of faith: as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. <hi>If the wicked re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, he ſhall liue.</hi> Luk. 13. <hi>Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> Ioh. 3. <hi>Except a man be borne againe of water and of the holy Ghoſt, he cannot enter into the Kingdome of God.</hi> The third part, he endeuoureth to proue thus: for that faith is not ſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to apprehend: or certainly, Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is not ſo apprehended by faith, that it is had indeed and inherent: but onely that it is in the mind after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of an obiect, apprehended by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vnderſtanding or will: But after this manner loue alſo and ioy do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>I anſwere. The aſſumption of the ſyllogiſme propoſed is falſe, as touching the third part or branch. For onely faith apprehendeth Chriſts ſatisfaction vnto Iuſtification: becauſe by faith onely we can make full account, that Chriſt hath ſatisfied for vs, and by his ſatisfaction ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of God forgiueneſſe of ſinnes for vs. And in this very ſence faith onely is
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3055:50"/>ſaid to iuſtifie, becauſe it onely apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Chriſts ſatisfaction: for which onely, and not for our works alſo, god counteth vs for iuſt. And this anſwere is inough for ſoluting the Argument propounded. Yet in the meane time, the Reader is to be put in minde, as touching the firſt part of the aſſumption, that it is not denied by <hi>Iames</hi> of true faith, that it onely iuſtifieth, but this only he meaneth, that man is not iuſtified by a dead faith, but by a liuing faith, which of it ſelf bringeth forth good workes.</p>
                  <p>And although it bee not found ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly written, <hi>Faith onely iuſtifieth:</hi> yet is there found a ſentence of equall force, namely, <hi>A man is not iuſtified but by faith,</hi> Gal. 2.16.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, as touching the ſecond part of the aſſumption: it is falſe, that the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture requireth the condition of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vnto Iuſtification: as though none could be iuſtified without the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Neither can it be proued from that place, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. <hi>Except a man be borne againe:</hi> for Chriſt ſpeaketh not there of Baptiſme, but of the holy Ghoſt that regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: which hee compareth to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:3055:50"/>
                     <note place="margin">The <hi>4.</hi> principall Argument which hath three bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches. <hi>1.</hi> Branch.</note>The 4. Argument <hi>Bellarmine</hi> fetcheth from the maner of iuſtifying of faith. And this hee parteth into three. The firſt is: Faith iuſtifieth after the manner of a cauſe: therefore it iuſtifieth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. I denie the conſequence: For although faith iuſtifieth after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a cauſe; yet it iuſtifieth alone: for it iuſtifieth as an inſtrumentall cauſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending Chriſtes ſatisfaction, for which onely wee are iuſtified. And there is no other inſtrumentall cauſe whereby Chriſts ſatisfaction is apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
                  <p>The other Argument.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Branch.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <q>Faith is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning formall cauſe of Iuſtification: Therefore it iuſtifieth not onely. To proue the antecedent, theſe ſayings are brought. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>To him that beleeueth in him that iuſtifieth the vngodly, his faith is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for iuſtice.</hi> 1. Cor. 3. <hi>Other foundation can no man lay, &amp;c.</hi> Where by foundation, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would haue vnderſtood, faith in Chriſt. And the foundation is the beginning of the houſe: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo faith is the beginning of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. <hi>By faith purifying theyr hearts.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:3055:51"/>
And what is pureneſſe of heart (ſaith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>) but iuſtice either begun or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. I denie the antecedent: and I denie, that it can be proued by the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings alleadged. For <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. Faith is ſaid to be reputed for iuſtice, in this ſence, for that iuſtice is imputed vnto a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by faith. For ſo the Apoſtle there ſaith, in the words next ioyned to them, that <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid, <hi>The man is bleſſed to whom God impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth iuſtice,</hi> namely by faith: as we may perceiue by conferring of the words that go before: as alſo by conference of that phraſe ſo much vſed of <hi>Paul,</hi> wherein he ſaith, <hi>That God iuſtifieth man through faith, of faith, by faith.</hi> Now to iuſtifie and to impute iuſtice, are of equal force with the ſame Apoſtle. Next, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. by the name of <hi>foundation,</hi> is vnderſtood Chriſt, as the Apoſtle himſelf plainly affirmeth: that is to ſay, the doctrine of Chriſt, namely, of his perſon and office. For hee there handleth Chriſtian doctrine, and not iuſtification. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> therefore So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtically wreſteth the name <hi>foundation,</hi> vnto Iuſtification: as though he treated there of the foundation, that is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Iuſtification.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:3055:51"/>
Now, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. <hi>Peter</hi> faith, their hearts were purified by faith, becauſe by faith the hearts are certified, that the bloud of Chriſt purgeth vs from all ſinne: to wit ſo, as that no ſinne is imputed to vs. There fore pureneſſe of heart is euill reſtrained of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> vnto purenes or iuſtice inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: when as there is alſo pureneſſe or iuſtice imputed.</p>
                  <p>The third Argument ſtraieth from the queſtion propounded: for it conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a diuerſe thing; namely thus. Faith obtaineth forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, &amp; after a ſort alſo deſerueth it: therefore it iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth not, becauſe it apprehendeth the promiſe. The antecedent hee proueth from <hi>Luk.</hi> 7. where our Lord ſaith to the woman, <hi>Thy faith hath made thee ſafe.</hi> But if faith did onely receiue mercie, it could not rightly be ſaid to ſaue. For who wold ſay to a poore man, that onely reacheth out his hand for almes, thy hand hath got the almes? or who wold ſay to a ſick man, that with his hand taketh the medicine, Thy hand hath cured thee of thy diſeaſe?</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. It followeth not: Faith maketh ſafe, therefore it ſaueth by obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and deſeruing. For the word, <hi>make</hi> in generall noteth an efficient cauſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:3055:52"/>
And from the generall to the ſpecial, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence followeth not affirmatiuely. And how faith maketh ſafe, wee muſt learne out of the ſcripture: which decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the nature and force of faith in iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, no otherwiſe then by relation vnto Chriſts ſatisfaction, as the obiect which it apprehendeth and applieth to a man, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>By faith in his bloud.</hi> Gal. 2. <hi>Who hath loued me and giuen himſelf for me, &amp;c.</hi> And although no wiſe man would ſay, <hi>Thy hand hath got thy almes:</hi> yet might one rightly ſay to him that is enriched by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing almes: <hi>Thy hand hath made thee rich.</hi> For if he had not taken the almes, he had not bene enriched. So our faith hath not made for vs Chriſtes ſatisfaction: but yet by receiuing it, it enricheth and iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth vs. Finally when it is ſaid, <hi>Faith iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth,</hi> it is a * figuratiue ſpeech; to bee vnderſtood thus, <hi>God Iuſtifieth</hi> a beleeuer, becauſe of Chriſts ſatisfaction which he apprehendeth by faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> bringeth alſo other places of ſcripture to confirme his antecedent, namely, <hi>Rom</hi> 4. <hi>Abraham was comforted by faith, giuing glory to God, &amp;c. Therefore alſo was it counted vnto him for iustice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this place, the Apoſtle ſheweth the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3055:52"/>cauſe why <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iuſtice: <q>becauſe in beleeuing hee gaue glory to God. Therefore that faith pleaſed God, by which he was glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified: and therefore for deſert of that faith (which notwithſtanding was his gift and grace) he iuſtified <hi>Abraham.</hi> Alſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall call vpon the name of the Lord ſhall be ſaued. How ſhal they cal vpon him is whom they haue not beleeued? how ſhall they beleeue without a Preacher?</hi> Where S. <hi>Paul</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) as hee maketh the preaching of the word, the cauſe of faith: ſo hee maketh faith the cauſe of inuocation: and inuocation the cauſe of ſauing: that is, of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</hi>
                     </q> Whereby wee vnderſtand (ſaith he further) that faith by inuocation, obtaineth iuſtification. Faith therefore iuſtifieth not relatiuely, to wit, by accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Iuſtification offered. Laſtly, in the 11. to the <hi>Heb.</hi> the Apoſtle teacheth by many examples, that men pleaſe God by faith; &amp; by this, that faith is of great price and merit with God.</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Although that place <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. may ſeeme much to fauor <hi>Bellarmines</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion: yet if one look throghly into it, &amp; conſider the applying of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3055:53"/>vnto vs. Which immediatly followeth, he ſhall ſee, the cauſall coniunction <hi>dio, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> not to be ſo much referred vnto that effect of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> faith, to wit, glorifying of God, as vnto the truth of his faith: which truth is ſignified by that effect. For in applying <hi>Abrahams</hi> example, hee doth not now mention ſtrong faith: ſuch as that of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> was: but ſimply true faith to wit, wherby we beleeue that God gaue Ieſus for our ſinnes, and raiſed him vp for our Iuſtification. The place <hi>Rom.</hi> 10 ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not of Iuſtification, but of ſaluation: that is glorification. Which although it be obtained by inuocation proceeding of faith: yet is it not obtained by the merit of faith, but by Gods grace and the way that he hath preſcribed. Laſtly, although out of <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. it is manifeſt that faith is of great price with God: yet hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not, that wee by faith do merit Gods benefits. For as other the benefites of God, ſo faith it ſelfe alſo is Gods free gift, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The <hi>5.</hi> prin cipal argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which hath <hi>2.</hi> branches.</note>There remaineth the laſt argument: which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith is taken from two principles: of which the one is, that the formal cauſe of Iuſtification is Iuſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally inherent in vs: the other, that good works are neceſſarie to ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:3055:53"/>
Before wee ſee how <hi>Bellarmine</hi> dooth reaſon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe principles; it is meet firſt to put in minde, that that firſt principle is falſe, euen by <hi>Bellarmines</hi> owne teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Booke of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chapt. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> For elſe-where he ſaith, The formall cauſe of Iuſtification conſiſteth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of that inherent iuſtice. But infuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iuſtice, is not the inherent iuſtice it ſelfe. But now let vs ſee how he reaſoneth from theſe principles.</p>
                  <p>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt principle he reaſoneth thus:</p>
                  <q>Vnto the infuſion of iustice are more acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons required then the action of faith: But Iuſtification is the infuſion of iuſtice: Therfore vnto Iuſtification are required moe actions then the action of faith: And by conſequence, onely faith Iuſtifieth not, after the manner of diſpoſition.</q>
                  <p>I anſwere. Firſt <hi>Bellarmine</hi> here depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the queſtion: not oppugning the opinion of the profeſſors of the Goſpell, but a Popiſh fiction. For the profeſſors of the Goſpel, when they ſay, that faith one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iuſtifieth, do not meane, that it iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth onely by way of diſpoſition, but by way of apprehenſion: as hath already b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> often declared. Then the aſſumption is falſe: as we haue ſhewed before. Beſides, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> agreeth not with himſelf: who
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3055:54"/>now affirmeth, that the action of faith is fore-required vnto Iuſtification; alſo that it diſpoſeth vnto Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before he ſaid,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1</hi> Booke of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chap. <hi>13.2.</hi> Booke Chapt. <hi>4.</hi> Of grace and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will. <hi>1.</hi> Booke. Chap. <hi>6.</hi> The latter Branch.</note> that <hi>Faith iuſtifieth as the beginning and firſt roote of Iuſtification:</hi> and afterward he maketh faith, part of the formall cauſe of <hi>Iustification,</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>That faith is not the whole formal cauſe of Iuſtification.</hi> And in an other place, <hi>that the formall cauſe of Iuſtification conſiſteth in faith, hope and charnie.</hi> Is part of the forme there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, fore required for the obtaining of the forme?</p>
                  <p>Now fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other principle, he draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this argument.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>If faith only did iuſtifie, it ſhuld only ſaue alſo. But it doth not only ſaue: becauſe good works are alſo neceſſarie to ſaluation. Therefore it onely doth not Iustifie.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Although this argument at the firſt ſight haue a great ſhew: yet if it be throghly looked into, it will be ſound to be a<note n="*" place="margin">i. A falſe argument.</note> Paralogiſme, hauing foure terms by the <hi>homony<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> or double ſignification of the argument or middle cerme. For that <hi>Onely ſaue,</hi> in the propoſition, is to be vnderſtood ſpecially of ſaluation, which is by way of apprehenſion: but in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, it is vnderſtood generally of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3055:54"/>ſaluation which is any maner of way. For faith onely ſaueth as the inſtrumentall apprehending cauſe, to wit, by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending Chriſtes ſatisfaction, for which God ſaueth the beleeuer: but it doth not onely ſaue euery maner of way: for Gods grace and Chriſts ſatisfaction alſo ſaueth, but as the principall efficient cauſes: alſo good workes ſaue, but as the way by which God bringeth the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers vnto ſaluation. This double ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication being obſerued, I anſwere to the aſſumption, where it is ſaid, <hi>Faith ſaueth not onely.</hi> If this be vnderſtood generally, it is true: but then an other thing is aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med then was in the propoſition. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſaid in the propoſition, <hi>Faith onely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth:</hi> that is not vnderſtood generally, but ſpecially: to wit, by way of apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But if the aſſumption bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood ſpecially, as in the propoſition, namely, that faith onely ſaueth not by laying hold on Chriſts ſatisfaction; it is manifeſtly falſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:3055:55"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The proofe of the third part, recited, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</head>
                  <p>HItherto of the ſecond part of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſentence, wherein they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that faith onely iuſtifieth not. Now followeth the third part, wherein they diſpute, that Iuſtification ſtandeth not onely in forgiueneſſe of ſins. Which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> purpoſeth to proue thus.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>I</hi> Booke of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chap. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication conſiſteth alſo (ſaith he) in inward renuing. Therefore not in forgiueneſſe of ſinnes onely. Wee denie the antecedent. But to proue that, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> bringeth ſome places of ſcripture: which wee will conſider in order.</p>
                  <p>The firſt place is <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>Who was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</hi> That is, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: that we may walke in newneſſe of life.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer. This expoſition of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> is falſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding thoſe things which the Apoſtle diſtinguiſheth. For <hi>Paul</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in that Epiſtle to diſpute of renning of nature, or of ſanctification, at the ſixt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3055:55"/>chapter, hauing finiſhed the diſputation of iuſtification in the fift chapter. And the ſenſe of the place alleaged is: That Chriſt was deliuered vnto death for our ſinnes, that is, to purge our ſinnes by ſatisfaction, and was raiſed vp for our iuſtification: that is to ſay, that he might make knowen our iuſtification: to wit, that he hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it by his death for vs. For if he had not riſen from the dead, we ſhould yet be in our ſinnes: 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Wherefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is riſen againe, we know that we are no more in our ſinnes, but that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes, or our iuſtification is gotten for vs by Chriſts death.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond place is,<note place="margin">The <hi>2.</hi> place.</note> 
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>As ſinne reigned vnto death, ſo alſo grace reigneth by iuſtice vnto eternall life.</hi>
                     <q>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> reaſoneth thus. He oppoſeth iuſtice to ſin: and by iuſtice vnderſtandeth renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, from which works proceed of life, for that the oppoſition requireth. For ſinne is ſaid to haue reigned vnto death, becauſe it wrought deadly workes: contrariwiſe, therfore the grace of God is ſaid to reign by iuſtice vnto life, becauſe by iuſtice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, it worketh the works of life. And if inward renuing, which is the beginning of good works, be rightly called ruſtice,</q>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:3055:56"/>out of doubt Iuſtification muſt be conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in that renuing, and not in forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes onely.</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. A gaine <hi>Bellarmine</hi> brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a falſe expoſition. For the Apoſtle entreateth nothing in that Chapter, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing of nature: but afterward in the Chapter following. And the meaning of the place alleaged, by comparing it vnto the former, with which it agreeth, may be perceiued to be this. As <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his poſterite vnto death, becauſe being imputed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it brought death: that ſo the grace of God whereby he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth iuſtice to them that beleeue, for Chriſts ſatisfaction, reigneth in them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life eternall: becauſe iuſtice being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to them, bringeth life eternall.</p>
                  <p>The third place is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>Neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit your members as weapons of iniquitie to ſinne: but exhibit your ſelues to God, as liuing from the dead, and your members weapons of iuſtice to God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. This place ſpeaketh not of <hi>Iustification;</hi> the diſpute whereof the Apoſtle ended in the 5. Chapter: but treateth of ſanctification. Wherefore it maketh nothing to the matter.</p>
                  <p>The 4. place is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>The ſpirit li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth</hi>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:3055:56"/>
                     <q>
                        <hi>for Iuſtification: or</hi> (as it is in the Greek) <hi>the ſpirit of life for iustice: Bellarmine</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: Iuſtification or iuſtice, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to liue, and by this to worke, cannot be for giueneſſe of ſinnes onely: but ſome inward and inherent thing.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Againe he bringeth a falſe expoſition: for neither ſpeaketh he here of Iuſtification, but of ſanctification: as is manifeſt by the things before and after. And the meaning of the place is: that the ſpirit of God, dwelling in them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and are iuſtified by faith, quickneth them, as concerning ſtudy of iuſtice or good workes: ſo that now they ceaſe to giue themſelues to ſinne, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe doo ſtudie for iuſtice and good workes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The 5. place is <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>If there had bene a law giuen, that could haue giuen life: ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iuſtice had bene by the law.</hi> Here the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſheweth openly (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) that <hi>Iuſtice</hi> whereupon <hi>Iustification</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, is ſomething that giueth life to the ſoule: and conſtituteth it in motion and action.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I ſee not by what ſyllogiſme <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> gathereth this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence from the Apoſtles words. The meaning of the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3055:57"/>Apoſtle is: If the law could giue life to man, vnto whom it was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that is, could giue him ſtrength perfectly to fulfill or keep it: then ſhould mans iuſtice ariſe of the law: that is, man ſhould be iuſt, and counted of God for iuſt for the law by him obſerued. But by what force wil you conclude fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence, that iuſtification con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in that iuſtice which conſtituteth the ſoule in action, that is, in inherent iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice? Yea the contrary may rather be fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence concluded: namely, that iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conſiſteth not in that iuſtice: for that iuſtice, which is required vnto iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, namely, perfect obſeruation of the law, falleth not vnto man in this life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The ſixt place is,<note place="margin">6. Place.</note> 
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Be renued in the ſpirit of your minde, and put on the new man, which according to God is crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in iustice and holineſſe of truth.</hi> Where the Apoſtle calleth renuing, iuſtice and holineſſe.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. This place alſo maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the matter: ſeeing it ſpeaketh not of iuſtification, but of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: neither of the iuſtice of faith, but of the iuſtice of workes: which although it be not perfect, and euery way abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3055:57"/>in the regenerate, ſo as to anſwer in euery part to the law of God: yet is it true and ſincere, and not feigned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Three reaſons.</note>To theſe arguments <hi>Bellarmine</hi> addeth three reaſons, which he calleth naturall: which alſo we will conſider.</p>
                  <p>The firſt reaſon is.<note place="margin">1.</note> 
                     <q>Iuſtification with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt is a certaine motion from ſinne vnto iuſtice: and hath it name from the thing whereunto it leadeth, as all other the like motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; inlightning, warning, &amp;c. True iuſtification therefore cannot be vnderſtood, except ſome iuſtice be gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſides forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: euen as it can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> either be true inlightning, nor true warming: if when darkneſſe is driuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, or cold expelled, there follow no light, and no heate in the ſubiect the body.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Iuſtification, it is in deed a kind of motion from ſinne to iuſtice, but not ſuch as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> feigneth: to wit, ſuch as inlightning and warning be. For it is not the motion of expelling ſinne and infuſing iuſtice: for this motion in ſcripture is not called Iuſtification, but <hi>Regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Renouation, Sanctification.</hi> But it is the motion of forgiuing or remitting ſinne, and imputing iuſtice. Now forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3055:58"/>of ſinne, and imputing of iuſtice, differ onely in name, indeed they are the ſame: as appeareth by the Apoſtles words <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.7. as we haue declared elſwhere. And what other thing it is to driue out darkneſſe, but to bring in light? alſo what els, to expell cold, but to put in warmth? Vnaptly therfore doth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> feigne, that darkeneſſe may be driuen away, and cold expelled, although there follow no light nor heate in the ſubiect body.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond reaſon.<note place="margin">2.</note> Iuſtification (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) is not therefore onely giuen vs of God, that we may eſcape the paines of hell, but alſo that we may get the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of heauenly life. But ſurely, onely forgiueneſſe of ſinnes deliuereth from paine, doth not giue glorie. Which thing we ſee daily in ciuil iudgements. For they that are quitted by the iudge, are deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from death, but they get not new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards for this alone, that they are iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not to haue bene, or not to be guiltie.</p>
                  <p>I deny the aſſumption. For remiſſion of ſinnes doth not onely deliuer from paine, to wit, eternall death; but alſo bringeth glorie or eternall life. The reaſon of which thing is this, that remiſſion of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3055:58"/>ſinnes, wherein mans iuſtification conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, is remiſſion of all ſinnes: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not onely of ſinnes of committing, but alſo of ſinnes of omitting: whereby it commeth, that he to whome God forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſinnes, is ſo accounted of, as if he had not only committed nothing which God hath forbidden in his law: but alſo, omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing of that which he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: and therefore, as if he had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly fulfilled the law of God. Now where the perfect fulfilling of the law is, there alſo is life; according to that, <hi>The man that doeth theſe thinges ſhall liue in them.</hi> Moreouer, the example of ciuil iudgement which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> bringeth, proueth not his aſſumption: becauſe that abſolution is vnlike to the abſolution of God. For this is vniuerſall, to wit from all ſinnes againſt the law of God: but that is particular or ſpecial; to wit, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine crime or crimes, againſt the politick lawes. Notwithſtanding, the ciuil Iudge giueth vnto him whome he hath quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from certaine crimes, thoſe rewards which hee hath promiſed to the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, namely, preſeruation in life and defence; although hee giue him no new and ſingular rewards which hee hath
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3055:59"/>promiſed onely to certaine vertuous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits. And ſo God giueth eternall life as a reward to thoſe, vnto whome he hath promiſed it, to wit, vnto thoſe that keepe his law: ſuch as he accounteth all thoſe, whoſe ſinnes he hath forgiuen.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>The third reaſon. <hi>Iuſtification of enemies maketh friends, children, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>, citizens with Saints, of the houſhold of God, heyres of his kingdome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Onely for giueneſſe of ſinnes, maketh not men ſuch:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therefore onely forgiueneſſe of ſinnes is not iustification.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The aſſumption he would proue thus: For one is not worthy of loue for this only that his dets are forgiuen him when hee cannot pay them. Neither is hee ſtraight-way made a ſonne, a citizen, or of the houſhold, or an heyre: who by the iudges clemencie vndergoeth not the puniſhment, whereto he was iuſtly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>I deny the aſſumption. And I proue the contrary by the Apoſtles words, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.5.6.7. <hi>He bath predestinate vs to be adopted through Ieſus Chriſt, vnto himſelfe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the good pleaſure of his will: To the praiſe of the glory of his grace, wherewith he
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3055:59"/>hath made vs accepted in that Beloued; by whome wee haue redemption through his bloud, the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes.</hi> If thou askeſt how God hath adopted vs for ſonnes, and ſo for heyres of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? alſo, how he hath made vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, that is, friends and beloued? the Apoſtle anſwereth: <hi>By Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> alſo, <hi>In that</hi> (his) <hi>beloued:</hi> and declaring this ſame thing, he faith, <hi>that in him or by him we haue redemption through his bloud, the for giuenes of ſinnes.</hi> Therefore the Apoſtle ſheweth no other thing <hi>by which</hi> we are made the friends of God, then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes: neither any other thing <hi>for which,</hi> then the redemption made by the bloud of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>The proofe which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the aſſumption, hath no force, for the manner of dealing with God and with men is vnlike. Men are not ſo affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that they will ſtraightway vouchſafe to heape benefits on him, to whom they haue forgiuen offences: but God, to whomſoeuer he forgiueth offences for Chriſt, them he proſecuteth which eternal fauour for his ſake: and thereupon hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his benefits on them, though vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:3055:60"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The proofe of the fourth part, recited and refuted.</head>
                  <p>NOw remayneth the fourth and laſt part of the Papiſts ſentence, That iuſtification confiſteth not in imputation of Chriſtes iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>This firſt he would proue by this,<note place="margin">I. <hi>Proofe.</hi>
                     </note> that <q>it is neuer read in the ſcripture, that Chriſtes iuſtice is imputed to vs: or, that we are iuſt, by Chriſtes iuſtice imputed to vs.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before I anſwere this argument, I will firſt ſhew in what ſenſe theſe things be ſpoken of the profeſſors of the Goſpell, whome <hi>Bellarmine</hi> oppugneth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when they ſay, That Chriſtes iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is imputed to vs, they vnderſtand, the iuſtice gotten by Chriſtes death. Therefore this they meane: That iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is imputed to vs of God, or, we are counted of God iuſt, for the death of Chriſt, whereby hee hath ſatisfied his iudgement for our ſinnes. Which is all one as if they ſhould ſay, that Chriſtes ſatisfaction is of God imputed vnto vs for
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3055:60"/>iuſtice. This appeareth by <hi>Caluins</hi> words in his third booke of Inſtir.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Booke of Iustific. chapt. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> chap. 11.5.3. Which place <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe citeth: namely, <hi>To iustifie, is nothing elſe, but to acquite from guiltineſſe, as being of appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued innocency, him that is guiltie or ſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. When as therefore God iustifieth vs by Christes interceſſion, he doth not acquite vs, by approuing of our owne innocencie, but by imputation of iustice: that we are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iuſt in Chriſt, which are not ſo in our ſelues.</hi> Behold he ſaith, <hi>God iustifieth vs by Christes interceſſion, that is, for Chriſtes interceſſion:</hi> vnder which name is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended ſatisfaction. Alſo, <hi>He acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs by imputation of iustice,</hi> or, in as much as hee imputeth iuſtice vnto vs: namely for that interceſſion and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Chriſt. Whereby wee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that <hi>Caluine</hi> maketh the formall cauſe of iuſtification, to be imputation of iuſtice, which otherwhere he calleth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>Now the meaning of the words being declared, I anſwere to <hi>Bellarmines</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and ſay, that it is not neceſſarie that thoſe very wordes, <hi>Christes iustice is imputed to vs,</hi> be read in the ſcripture: but that it is ynough, if thoſe things
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:3055:61"/>be read, from which this ſentence may by good conſequence be drawen. And ſuch we read: namely where it is ſaid, that <hi>faith is imputed to man for iustice,</hi> and, <hi>that iustice is imputed to man, Rom.</hi> 4.5.6. Now ſeeing theſe phraſes be diuerſe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be both of them proper: we muſt conſider which is proper, and which figuratiue. To ſpeake properly, a thing is ſaid to be imputed to one, which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath not done, or which is not in himſelfe: and contrariwiſe, that is ſaid not to be imputed, which one hath done, or which is in him. Therefore when iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is ſaid to be imputed to ſinfull man, it is a proper ſpeech: us alſo when it is ſaid, that ſinne is not imputed to a ſinner. It is therfore improperly ſaid, that <hi>To him</hi> that beleeueth, faith is imputed for iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and therefore this is to be vnfolden by a proper ſpeech: to wit, that <hi>To him</hi> that beleeueth, iuſtice is imputed: or, he that beleeueth is counted for iuſt, by faith: as elſewhere the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The beleeuer is iustified by faith.</hi> Which that it may more fully be vnderſtood, it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that the nature of faith be declared by his obiect whereon it leaneth, or which it apprehendeth for iuſtice. For that is the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:3055:61"/>thing for which the beleeuer is iuſtified, or iuſtice is imputed to him: or finally which is imputed to him for iuſtice by faith. And that obiect of faith is Chriſtes ſatisfaction: as appeareth by the Apoſtles words, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Whom God hath ſet forth a reconciliation by faith in his bloud.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſpeake properly, iuſtice is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vs for Chriſtes ſatisfaction by faith: becauſe we apprehend that by faith: or Chriſtes ſatisfaction is imputed to vs for iuſtice by faith: that is, in as much as it is apprehended by faith.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Proofe.</hi>
                     </note> he would proue the ſame thing by this, <q>that no neceſſitie can be alleadged of that ſort of imputation.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But, ſay I, there is manifeſt neceſſitie: namely our ſinnes which cannot be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done: but leaſt we be damned for them, it is neceſſary that they be not imputed to vs, but couered: which is no other thing, then to haue iuſtice imputed to vs: as appeareth by the Apoſtles wordes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.7. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Bleſſed is that man to whom God imputeth iustice. Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiuen, and whoſe ſinnes are couered: bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord ſhall not impute ſinne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> laboureth to confirme his argument, thus.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:3055:62"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If this imputation were neceſſarie: it ſhould therefore cheefly be neceſſary, for that man after forgiueneſſe of ſinne is yet verily a ſinner, to wit, his ſinne being couered, not taken away.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But this cauſe of neceſſitie hath no place. Becauſe by forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, ſinne is vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly taken away, that it is not: (for proofe whereof, he heapeth together many testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſcripture.)</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore this imputation is not neceſſary.</hi> I anſwere. Firſt, the propoſition is falſe: for although imputation of iuſtice be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for man, yet is it not therefore neceſſary, for that man after forgiueneſſe of ſinne is yet verily a ſinner: as though imputation of iuſtice were done after forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. For remiſſion of ſinnes, and imputation of iuſtice, are one and the ſame thing: as appeareth by the Apoſtles words, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.6. where theſe two are taken as equiualent, for <hi>Iustice to be imputed to man;</hi> and <hi>iniquities to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen a man.</hi> Yet is it true, that imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of iuſtice is neceſſary for a man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is a ſinner. Then, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confirmeth his aſſumption by a falſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: to wit, that by forgiueneſſe of ſins, ſinne is vtterly taken away, that it is not. For ſinne is taken away by forgiueneſſe;
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3055:62"/>not ſo as that it is not, but that it is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, but couered: as <hi>Dauid</hi> expreſly teacheth in that place which the Apoſtle citeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.7.8. in theſe words, <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiuen, and whoſe ſinnes are couered: bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord ſhal not impute ſin.</hi> Behold, if thou askeſt what it is to haue iniquities or ſins forgiuen? <hi>Dauid</hi> anſwereth: It is to haue ſins <hi>couered,</hi> that they come not into the ſight of God, as iudge. Alſo, it is to haue ſinne <hi>not imputed</hi> of the Lord: to wit, that man be puniſhed for his ſinne, as he hath deſerued. Wherefore we may not thinke, that in thoſe places of ſcripture (thoſe I meane that ſpeake of iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath heaped together, a diuerſe thing is taught: ſeeing it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that the holy Ghoſt contradicteth not himſelfe. Further, vnto that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from the oppoſition of <hi>Adam</hi> vnto Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> thinketh, will admit no anſwere at all: we haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered<note n="*" place="margin">Before in the ſecond chapter of this booke, in the ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> before. <hi>Bellarmines</hi> third argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If faith, hope and loue, can be perfect in this life: the imputation of Chriſtes iuſtice is not neceſſary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the antecedent is true:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>Proofe.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Therefore alſo the conſequent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:3055:63"/>
I anſwere. The propoſition is falſe. For firſt, that imputation of iuſtice be not neceſſary for man; it is not ynough, that faith, hope and loue, <hi>can be</hi> perfect in this life, but it behoueth that <hi>they be</hi> perfect. Then, though it be graunted that perfect faith, hope and loue, befall ſome (as the Martyrs) in this life: yet neuertheleſſe is imputation of iuſtice neceſſary for them, for ſinnes committed before the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe vertues. For we cannot ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie God for them, by the duties of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues that folow; ſeeing they are owing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. Therefore for old debts another ſatisfaction is needfull. And God cannot be ſatisfied for ſinnes, but by ſuffering the puniſhment of them. And this hath Chriſt ſuffered for them that beleeue, &amp; ſo hath ſatisfied for their ſinnes: which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction is imputed to them for iuſtice: and this imputation is needfull for them: ſeeing they cannot but by it be counted for iuſt, and worthy of eternall life: yea, iuſtifying faith, whether perfect or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, doth in any wiſe require imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iuſtice: ſeeing it iuſtifieth no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, then in as much as it apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Chriſts ſatisfaction, which by the grace of God is imputed for iuſtice to him that beleeueth.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:3055:63"/>
                     <p>In expoſition of the fourth argument, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alloweth of the Goſpellers ſentence, at leaſt in part: in that he ſaith, it is right if it be ſo vnderſtood: that Chriſts iuſtice is imputed to vs, that is, Chriſtes merits, becauſe they are giuen vnto vs: and we can offer them to God the Father for our ſinnes: becauſe Chriſt hath taken vpon him the burden of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying for vs, and reconciling vs to God the Father. Yet he denyeth, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes iuſtice it ſo imputed vnto vs, that we are called, and be formally iuſt by it, and that he would proue thus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When there be two contrary formes in any, the one inherent, the other outward: without doubt the abſolute denomination is taken from the inherent forme, rather then from the outward.</hi> For if one ſhould put a white garment vpon a black-moore, he could not rightly ſay, This black-moore is white: but contrary wiſe it might right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſaid, this Moore is black; becauſe the proper and inherent blackneſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth more vnto him, then that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward whiteneſſe fetched from an other thing.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But in man by the doctrine of imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iustice there are made two contrary formes, the one inherent, namely Iniustice:
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:3055:64"/>the other outward, namely, inputed iuſtice. Wherewith man by apprehenſion is cloathed as with a garment.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therfore man to whom iuſtice is imputed, is rather to be named vniuſt of the inherent forme, then iuſt of the outward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer vnto the propoſition. Althogh that denomination be vſuall with men: yet God in this affaire foloweth a diuerſe: reaſon in his word: ſaying both; to wit, that faith is imputed vnto vs for iuſtice, or that iuſtice is imputed to vs, to wit by faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.6. and that we are iuſtified by faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. And ſurely, when as we are ſo far forth iuſt before God, as iuſtice is imputed to vs, as <hi>Paul</hi> in the place allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. doth teach: it is rightly ſaid, that we by imputed iuſtice, be and are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med formally iuſt.</p>
                  <p>Now to the aſſumption. In man to whom iuſtice is imputed, it is graunted there is vniuſtice inherent: but it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, vniuſtice cleauing vnto him by ſinnes already committed, and not a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of doing vniuſtly. For to whom faith is giuen, that by it iuſtice is imputed to him and committed ſinnes are forgiuen: to him withall, is giuen a purpoſe to liue iuſtly, and to auoyd ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:3055:64"/>
                     <q>The 5. Argument.<note place="margin">5. <hi>Proof.</hi>
                        </note> If Chriſts iuſtice were truly imputed vnto vs, that by it we were counted and thought iuſt, euen as if it were our owne inward and formall iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: ſurely we ought to be counted and thought no leſſe iuſt then Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Then ought wee to be called and counted redeemers and ſauiours of the world, and to receiue other ſuch names and attributes of the like ſort: which is moſt abſurd.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. I denie the conſequence. For by Chriſts iuſtice which is imputed to vs, is vnderſtood the obedience of death, wherby he ſatisfied for our ſinnes, and ſo brought vs euerlaſting iuſtice (as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaketh.) This obedience I ſay, is imputed to vs for iuſtice: ſo that we are eſteemed of God, as if our ſelues had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it. Neither dooth it follow from hence, that wee ſhould be called and counted redeemers and ſauiours of the world: both for that Chriſts ſuffering is ſo imputed to euery beleeuer, as if hee had ſuffered for himſelfe, and not for others: as alſo becauſe that any may be called the redeemer and ſauiour of the world, it is not inogh that he be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſuffer for the world, but it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:3055:65"/>that he be meete to ſatisfie God by his ſuffering for the world: and vnto this is required, that he be not onely man, but a holy man, and beſides that, God.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>The ſixt Argument.<note place="margin">6. <hi>Proofe.</hi>
                        </note> Chriſt hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored vs that which we loſt in <hi>Adam.</hi> But in <hi>Adam</hi> we loſt not imputed iuſtice: neither to be in Gods image and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by imputation: but true inherent iuſtice, by which we were truly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to God. Therefore we receiue by Chriſt true iuſtice and likeneſſe of God, and not onely an outward imputation. Thus ſaith <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Which things that they may the more eaſily be iudged of, we will reſolue them. And they be two ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſmes. The firſt is this.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That which we loſt in</hi> Adam, <hi>is reſtored vs by Chriſt: In</hi> Adam <hi>we loſt not imputed iustice, Therefore, imputed iustice is not restored vs by Chriſt.</hi> The ſecond ſyllogiſme is this. <hi>That which we loſt in</hi> Adam, <hi>is restored vs by Chriſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> out iustice we loſt in</hi> Adam. <hi>Therefore, inherent iustice is restored vs by Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:3055:65"/>
I anſwere to the laſt firſt. I grant all the latter ſyllogiſme: but the concluſion of it, is far from the queſtion proponed. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Chriſt hath reſtored vs inherent iuſtice, in regenerating and renuing vs to the Image of God by the holy Ghoſt; in this life as beginning; in the next<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: yet that letteth not, why he ſhould not impute iuſtice to vs, wherby we may ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God. As touching the firſt ſyllogiſme, it firſt of all is faultie in the ſtorme, becauſe it hath a negatiue minor in the firſt figure. Then, the concluſion is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the queſtion proponed. For it is not asked, whether that iuſtice be reſtored vs which was imouted to vs in <hi>Adam</hi> before he fel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but it is demanded, whether iuſtice be imputed to vs, that is, whether wee be eſteemed of God for iuſt, becauſe of Chriſts ſatisfaction. Thirdly, the minor <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omimu</hi> in the aſſumption is doubtfull. For imputed iuſtice there may bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode either of the iuſtice which may bee ſaide to bee imputed to vs in <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall: or of the iuſtice which wee ſay now is imputed to vs for Chriſts ſatisfaction. In the firſt ſence, the aſſumption is true: but then there be foure <hi>termini,</hi> for that <hi>minor terminus</hi> in the concluſion is manifeſtly vnderſtood
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:3055:66"/>of the iuſtice which is ſaid to be imputed to vs in <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall: as is plaine by the word <hi>Reſtore.</hi> And in the latter ſenſe the aſſumption is falſe: for wee loſt ſurely in <hi>Adam</hi> that iuſtice which now is imputed vnto vs for Chriſts ſatisfaction. For by the diſobedience of <hi>Adam</hi> we were made vniuſt; and again, by Chriſts obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence we are made iuſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. &amp; that by imputation of iuſtice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The 7. Argument.<note place="margin">7. <hi>Proof.</hi>
                        </note> If by Chriſts iuſtice imputed to vs, wee may truly be called iuſt, &amp; ſons of God: then might Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by our iniuſtice imputed to him, be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called a ſinner, &amp; (that which the ſoule trembleth to think) the ſonne of the diuel. For the aduerſaries graunt that ſin was ſo imputed to Chriſt, as iuſtice is imputed to vs. But the conſequence is not true; but blaſphemous, ſacriligious, and repugnant to all the ſcripture; wherein Chriſt is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where preached to be holy, innocent, immortall, vnpolluted, and moſt iuſt. Therefore neither is the antecedent true.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. There be foure <hi>termini,</hi> for the doubtfulnes of the word <hi>truly:</hi> which in the propoſition is vnderſtood of the truth of imputation, but in the aſſumption of the truth of inherence. For after the manner of inherence, Chriſt was not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:3055:66"/>a ſinner, but truly holy, innocent, &amp;c. Yet after the manner of imputation he was tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſinner: for our ſins were truly imputed vnto him of God, when as for them he was truly made a curſe or execration, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. that is, accurſed: as is there declared, when it is added: For it is written, <hi>Curſed is euery one that hangeth on tree.</hi> Now none is accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto God, but for ſin; that is, in as much as either he is a ſinner, or ſo reputed. And ſo alſo may be expounded, and it ſeemeth ſhould bee expounded that place, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 <hi>Him which knew no ſin, he made ſin for vs: that we might be made the iuſtice of God in him.</hi> For although it be a ſound expoſition, that God made Chriſt a ſacrifice for ſin: yet the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſeemeth to require that it be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>he made him a ſinner:</hi> namely by imputing our ſins vnto him: for ſo are we made iuſtice in him, whiles we are made iuſt by imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſuffering.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> vrgeth this argument: &amp; from that compariſon of the imputation of Chriſts iuſtice, and the imputation of our vniuſtice, he proceedeth to reaſon thus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If we were truly vncleane and wicked, euen after iuſtification: although Chriſtes iuſtice were imputed vnto vs, yet were we not to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led iuſt, but vnrighteous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:3055:67"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But the ſcripture calleth vs iuſt and holy. Gods ſonnes and heires after the lauer of regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and renouation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>We are not therefore iuſtified by imputation of iuſtice, but by iuſtice inherent and abiding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>The propoſition he confirmeth by the compariſon before ſpoken of.</p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Firſt, there be 4. <hi>termini:</hi> for it is one thing to be called iuſt after Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, as it is ſet downe in the propoſition: and an other thing, <hi>to be called iuſt after the lauer of regeneration and renouation,</hi> as is ſet downe in the aſſumption. Then the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion followeth not of the premiſſes, no not though the ſame argument be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the aſſumption, which is contained in the propoſition, as namely, if it be ſaid, <hi>But the ſcripture calleth vs iuſt after Iuſtification.</hi> But this concluſion followeth of thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes: <hi>Therfore after Iuſtification we are not truly vncleane and wicked:</hi> Which no profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of the Goſpell denieth. For after the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of faith, we are truly cleane and godly by imputation; yea and moreouer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, by inherence of godlineſſe, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun onely: for iuſtifying faith, doth neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily bring with it ſtudy of godlineſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The 8. Argument.<note place="margin">8. <hi>Proofe.</hi>
                        </note> Chriſt in the ſong of Songs, is compared to a Bridegroome:
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:3055:67"/>and the Church or iuſtified ſoule, is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a Bride. And that Bride is ſaid to bee faire, with the bewtie inherent to her ſelfe, not with the bewtie of the Bridegroome imputed to her. For therfore vnto the Bride is giuen the bewtie proper to women; and vnto the Bridegroome, the bewtie proper to men: that we may vnderſtand, that the bewtie of Chriſt is one, the bewtie of the Church or iuſtified ſoule is an other. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer it would be moſt abſurd, if an heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bridegroome, and one that is moſt faire indeed, ſhould haue a filthy Bride, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decked outwardly with ſome precious garment of a man.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Chriſtes Bride, the Church, in the Song of Songs, confeſſeth that ſhee is black, &amp; withall affirmeth that ſhe is come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Chap. 1.5. By that confeſsion ſhee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth her filthineſſe or natiue defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, that is, ſin: but by that affirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhe ſetteth forth the bewtie receiued from the Bridegroome. And that bewtie is double: the one of iuſtice imputed, the other of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice infuſed: but this is imperfect in this life. Wherefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth falſly lay it to the Goſpellers charge, as if they thought, that Chriſts Bride euen iuſtified, ſhould yet be filthy: or faire onely by imputation of iuſtice. Moreouer, although Chriſtes Bride
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:3055:68"/>be faire, euen by iuſtice inherent to her: yee hence it followeth not, that ſhe is not iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by iuſtice imputed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The 9. Argument.<note place="margin">9. <hi>Proof.</hi>
                        </note> If by Iuſtification the heart be prepared vnto the ſight of God: then is true cleanneſſe conferred by it, and not imputatiue. But the antecedent is true: therefore alſo the conſequent. The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the propoſition is proued by a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile. For as the eye being indeed vncleane, though it be counted moſt cleane and pure, cannot ſee the ſunne: ſo neither can an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane heart, though it be counted cleane, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſee God.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth ſophiſtically oppoſe, true &amp; imputed cleannes: as though the cleanneſſe which is imputed vnto vs by faith, were not true cleanneſſe. Alſo by the reſt of his diſputation it appeareth, that hee by true cleanneſſe, vnderſtandeth inherent cleanneſſe. But the conſequence of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is falſe. For although it be needfull to haue an eye truly and habitually cleane for to ſee withall: and by Iuſtification the heart is after a ſort prepared to ſee God: yet is not inherent cleanneſſe conferred by it, but by regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Euen as by taking away the putrified matter, a wound is prepared vnto the ſcarre: yet is there no forte confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by it for the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to cloſe togither, but
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:3055:68"/>by the plaiſter which is laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wound being purged of the putrified matter. For God firſt by Iuſtification remoueth from man the filth and vncleanneſſe of ſin: then by regeneration endueth him with faith &amp; ſtudie of godlineſſe: that by faith hee may be made more ſure of his Iuſtification, and may begin to ſee God: &amp; by ſtudie of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe cleaue vnto him, vntil he come to ſee him fully in the other life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The 10. Argument. Chriſt ſuffered,<note place="margin">10. <hi>Proof.</hi>
                        </note> that he might ſanctifie his people by his bloud: <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. that he might ſanctifie his Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. that he might cleanſe for himſelfe a people acceptable. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. And the Lord himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17. I ſanctifie my ſelfe for them, that they alſo may be ſanctified in the truth. But if Chriſt haue ſanctified his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not truly, but onely by imputation, hee hath ſuffered and died in vaine, &amp; he could not performe that he deſired. For to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſanctifie, &amp; to ſanctifie in the truth, doth not ſignifie onely to be willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer from the puniſhment of ſinne, or to be willing that we ſhould be counted for Saints, though indeed we be not ſo: but to be willing to effect that, wherby we may be truly Saints, cleane and immaculate. Thus farre <hi>Bellarmine.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Syllogiſme is to be formed thus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:3055:69"/>
                     <hi>If Chriſt haue not ſanctified his people truly, but onely imputatiuely he ſuffered in vaine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But he ſuffered not in vaine. Therefore, He hath ſanctified his people truly and not onely imputatiuely.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwere. Againe, <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>imputatiuely</hi> are ſophiſtically oppoſed. Then, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is from the queſtion. For the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers confeſſe, that Chriſt hath ſanctified his people, not onely imputatiuely, but alſo habitually: or, not onely by imputation of holineſſe, but alſo by reall beginning of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: for by his ſuffering, he obtained both benefites of God. But yet it followeth not from hence, that the iuſtification wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with man is iuſtified before God conſiſteth not in imputation of Iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note>Theſe things the Lord hath giuen me at this time to diſpute againſt <hi>Bellarmines</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſmes of Iuſtification. His graune that they may be a helpe vnto many to rid themſelues out of thoſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſmes.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3055:69"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
